<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certaine sermons, preached by the reuerend and iudicious diuine master Thomas Nevvhovse late preacher of Gods word in the citie of Norwich. And now set foorth for the vse and benefit of Gods people, by Robert Gallard, Master of Arts and minister in the same citie</title>
            <author>Newhouse, Thomas, d. 1611.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1614</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 207 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 91 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08129</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18493</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102789</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838551</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838551</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2933</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08129)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2933)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1147:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certaine sermons, preached by the reuerend and iudicious diuine master Thomas Nevvhovse late preacher of Gods word in the citie of Norwich. And now set foorth for the vse and benefit of Gods people, by Robert Gallard, Master of Arts and minister in the same citie</title>
                  <author>Newhouse, Thomas, d. 1611.</author>
                  <author>Gallard, Robert.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32], 144 [i.e. 142] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Felix Kingston for Edmund Weaver and William Welby,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1614.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Four sermons, the third and fourth of which have special dedicatory epistle, dated Nov. 15, 1613, and special title page, with same imprint as main title page, reading: Two sermons, preached by that reuerend and iudicious diuine master Thomas Nevvhouse, late preacher of Gods word in the citie of Norwich. And now set foorth for the vse and benefit of Gods people, by Robert Gallard Master of Arts, and minister in the same citie.</note>
                  <note>Pages 65-66 missing in number only.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Election (Theology) --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2933:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2933:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>CERTAINE SERMONS, PREACHED BY THAT Reuerend and Iudicious Diuine Maſter THOMAS NEVVHOVSE, late Preacher of Gods word in the Citie of <hi>Norwich.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AND NOW SET FOORTH for the vſe and benefit of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, by ROBERT GALLARD Maſter of Arts, and Miniſter <hi>in the ſame Citie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>ECCLESIAST. 12.11.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>The words of the wiſe are as goads and nailes faſtned by the Maſters of the aſſemblies, which are giuen from one ſhepheard.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>AT LONDON Imprinted by <hi>Felix Kingſton,</hi> for <hi>Edmund Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer</hi> and <hi>William Welby.</hi> 1614.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2933:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2933:2"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLI. MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter GEORGE COCK, Maior of that famous and well-gouerned</hi> Citie of Norwich, together with the <hi>Worſhipfull Companie of Sherifes and Aldermen his fellow brethren in the ſame Citie: R. G. wiſheth all true proſperitie.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Worſhipfull, that ſpeech of the Poet, <hi>viz. ſcribimus indocti doctique, &amp;c.</hi> was neuer ſo true as now in this our ſcribling age, wherein ſo many are poſſeſſed with a brainſicke humor of being ſeene in print. I touch not any of thoſe (the ſearcher of all hearts knoweth) whoſe writings are of good worth, and vſefull to helpe forward the ſpirituall building; yea,
<note place="margin">Iames 2.17.</note> rather I much bleſſe that God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of lights, whoſe ſpirit hath of late ſo clearely ſhined in the workes of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, for hereby the trueth which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:2933:3"/>(as an vnknowne treaſure) lay hid is notably diſcouered, error con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed, vertue much furthered in the hearts and liues of men. But of ſuch onely I ſpeake, who being bigge with conceit of their owne conceits, must needs vent and ſet them a broach, though neuer ſo froathie, and in truth being ballanced in the ſcoale of a iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious Reader, found altogether ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then vanitie it ſelfe. Their works I may fitly reſemble to the Spiders web, for though they ſeeme to be ſpun with ſome curioſitie, yet in truth they be deuoide of all ſubstance and ſolidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: or to the airie Meteors, for as they very ſuddenly vaniſh out of ſight, ſo theſe (being as it were of an airie nature) doe euen in the reading, <hi>quaſi abire in fumum.</hi> Alas, little is the gaine a man gets by them: with ſuch ſuperficiall and ſlightie ſtuffe our age ſo abounds, that many complaine of a ſacietie, yea of a ſurfit, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for my part I wiſh that men were more modest this way, and would keepe in their pennes from blotting ſo
<pb facs="tcp:2933:3"/>much paper in vaine; moſt excellent is the rule of <hi>Euripides</hi> for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>i.</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpeake that which is better then ſilence, or elſe keepe ſilent ſtill.</p>
                  <p>The workes which here I am bold, right Worſhipfull, to publiſh to the worlds view, are not (as in reading you ſhall ſee) any vaine or idle diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes ſauouring of an empty braine, but moſt heauenly and diuine truths, breathed forth by the breath of an holy and ſanctified heart: they bee a few of thoſe ſweete blasts, that were ſounded forth in your hearing, by that <hi>ſiluer ſounding trumpit:</hi> I meane the learned lectures of that famous and most iudicious diuine Master <hi>Thomas Newhouſe,</hi> late Preacher of Gods word among you: who (as you know) like a faithfull ſeruant of Chriſt, thought not his life too preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to lay downe in his Masters ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, but willingly as it were ſacrificed himſelfe to God in his miniſterie, and as the candle, ſpent himſelfe to giue you light.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:2933:4"/>
When I ſeriouſlie conſider how compleate this holy man of God was, how fitted and furniſhed with diuine gifts for his heauenly function, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not (and I thinke no more can you) but much bewaile) our grieuous loſſe; can a man lament the loſſe of his box full of precious and coſtly iewels, or a Marchant the wracke of his ſhippe fraught with earthen treaſure, then ſurely may we much more, the loſſe of this box, the wracke of this ſhip, ſo fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and fraught with ſuch ſpirituall and diuine riches? What a maſſe of knowledge God ſtored vp in this his earthen veſſell, your thurſday Lecture in part bewrayed, wherein he did v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually vent ſo much diuinitie, as that his learned brethren ſeldome went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way (by their owne confeſsion) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out inſight into ſome ſpeciall things they neuer knew before: and for his excellent <hi>skill in Caſe-diuinitie,</hi> whereby he was able to ſettle the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering and doubting <hi>Conſcience,</hi> I may truly ſay of him as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> doth of himſelfe,
<note n="*" place="margin">Iſaiah 52.4.</note> 
                     <hi>The Lord gaue him
<pb facs="tcp:2933:4"/>the tongue of the learned to ſpeake a word in ſeaſon to him that was weary.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Againe for that ſingular gift God gaue him in vnfoulding and explai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning moſt myſticall and infoulded truthes, in vnlooſing moſt intricate and knottie doubtes (whereof there bee many twixt vs and that Romiſh Church, as alſo for his marueilous dexteritie in ſelecting, contriuing, but eſpecially in acute and ſolid iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, who euer almost did heare him, but will acknowledge his excellencie in all theſe things with admiration?</p>
                  <p>And yet moreouer what a great meaſure of ſanctifying grace, it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the diuine ſpirit (which bloweth where it listeth) to beautifie this his inſtrument with, what rare and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent vertues did appeare and ſhine forth in the courſe of his life, it is not (I appeale to them that knew him) an eaſie thing for me to declare; I haue much muſed to ſee how <hi>aſſiduous</hi> he was in his painefull calling, how care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full alwaies to put men forward in the
<pb facs="tcp:2933:5"/>way of life, how careles of the world, not ſeeking the gaine thereof couete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſlie, nor the glorie thereof ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſlie, a vertue in theſe our times not commonly ſeene in ſo great meaſure, in men of ſo great gifts and learning. I neede not ſpeake of his meeke, lowly, courteous and affable carriage euen towards his inferiours; how wiſe and gracious he was in his behauiour, how graue, ſober, amiable and louely in all his demeanour, all ſuch can ſay that knew him, and I am ſure that none of you that knew and entirely loued him can eaſily forget, nor yet remember, without ſome ſigh or ſigne of ſorrow for the loſſe of ſo ſweet and ingenuous a friend. Thus out of the abundance of my hearty affection towards this man of God, I thought it meete accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that certain knowledge which I, and many of you yourſelues had of him, to record theſe things which tract of time would haue worne out and buried vp in the graue of obliui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; hope no man is ſo enutous as to grudge the dead ſhuld haue their due.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:2933:5"/>
Bethinking my ſelfe (Right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull) what courſe might bee taken to recouer the publique dammage which the Church hath ſuſtained in the death of this worthy man, I finde no way better then the publiſhing of ſuch manuſcripts as hee left behind him, among which I commend theſe few (as firſt fruits) to your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips patronage. The reaſons of my ſo doing be theſe, I know that his mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery (as it was meet it ſhould) was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong many of you much ſet by, you receiued him as an Angel of God, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed and heard him as an Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter one of a thouſand, you loued and reuerenced him in his life, and in his death lamented much (as cauſe you had) your publique loſſe, yea and ſtill I ſee how freſh his bleſſed name remaines among you, pleaſant as an oyntment powred out, ſweet as a bundle of myrrhe which ſendeth forth moſt fragrant ſmels; vpon theſe, and ſuch like grounds I am led to thinke, that theſe his endeuors cannot miſſe of your courteous acceptance
<pb facs="tcp:2933:6"/>and tuition, and therefore if I ſo farre preſume as to ſhroud theſe orphan writings vnder your protecting wing, I hope you will eaſily giue leaue to this my bold enterpriſe; wherein I haue but ſignified my duty to your ſelues, and my loue vnfained to him that is gone.</p>
                  <p>In theſe two treatiſes which in ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall wiſe I preſent vnto your view, you ſhall finde (Right Worſhipfull) theſe two pointes very ſoundly and plainely handled; the firſt is the moſt wiſe, and eternall decree of God, the ſecond is the freed, and alſo the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable eſtate of Gods childe, both of them matters of great waight and moment, needfull to bee knowne in ſome ſort of all, and no way vnworthy to be read and vnderſtood of the moſt worthie. I wiſh I might haue ſpoken ſomewhat of each of them: but leaſt I ſhould exceede the bounds of an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle, I will (your patience permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting) onely ſpend a few lines in ſetting downe how lawfull and meet a thing it is to preach &amp; publiſh the doctrine
<pb facs="tcp:2933:6"/>of predestination.</p>
                  <p>As it was horrible preſumption in the <hi>Bethſhemites</hi> to peere into Gods Arke, <hi>1. Sam. 6.19.</hi> So it hath been, and ſtill is eſteemed by many: for a man to diue though neuer ſo little into the doctrine of Gods decree, ſome holding it ſhould not bee medled with at all: others that it may be ſparing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly handled, but onely in ſchooles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the learned: but by their leaues they are much deceiued; for though we may not curiouſly ſearch into ſuch things as be hidden and wrapt vp in the ſecret counſell of God, yet are wee not forbidden to ſeeke the knowledge of thoſe things which bee reuealed. The Lord ſaith, Deuter. <hi>29.</hi> Secret things belong vnto God, let vs haue nothing to doe therewith: but fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he ſaith, reuealed things belong to vs and to our children; ſurely thoſe may we ſafely meddle with, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour to know; nay wee are bound both to know and publiſh, ſo be it wee keepe within the limits of wiſedome and ſobriety: for if God who is wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb facs="tcp:2933:7"/>it ſelfe, thinkes it a meete thing to open this doctrine to his Church, (as hee doth in the writings of the Prophets and Apostles) how can we conceale it without guilt of ſacrilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous follie? Shall wee bee ſo bold as to ſeale vp that which God hath opened? God forbid. But how iniurious they bee to the Church of God, who would haue this doctrine ſmothered from the people, and canuaſed onely in ſchooles of learning, will eaſily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, if we doe but conſider the great good it brings to the people of God, being perſpicuouſly and plainely taught. Our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith, Luke <hi>10.</hi> Reioyce in this, that your names are written in heauen: which place importes, that the enrolling our names in the booke of life: <hi>i.</hi> electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is a matter of great ioy. And in the <hi>6.</hi> of Ioh. <hi>3.</hi> All thoſe ſaith Chriſt, that the father hath giuen mee; <hi>i.</hi> in election, ſhal come vnto me, and thoſe that come to me I caſt not away; <hi>i.</hi> they ſhal not periſh. So that a beleeuer may hence aſſure himſelfe, that being ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
<pb facs="tcp:2933:7"/>bee cannot periſh. Were it not much then (by concealing this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of predeſtination) to depriue Gods people of this ioy, of this comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table aſſurance?</p>
                  <p>Againe, in this doctrine of Gods decree, ſoundly and plainely taught, a beleeuer ſhall finde that his appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſaluation is not grounded vpon any thing in himſelfe, neither his will, nor faith, nor works, nor wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe foreſeene, but onely the good will and pleaſure of God. As Epheſ. <hi>1.5.</hi> Who hath predeſtinated vs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the good pleaſure of his will, to the praiſe of the glory of his grace; now were it not ſinfull to hide from people this heauenly doctrine, whereby they are taught to aſcribe all the glory of their ſaluation to the free fauour and loue of God in their ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction? Yes ſurely. Yet moreouer in our predeſtination to eternall life, wee plainely ſee as in a glaſſe an Ocean ſea of Gods loue and fauour towards vs, in that God paſsing by ſo many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands as veſſels of wrath ſet apart to
<pb facs="tcp:2933:8"/>perpetuall ſhame, would ſelect and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point vs to the obtaining of eternall life by Ieſus Chriſt. Now how can it be (loue being the loadſtone of loue) but that the liuely ſenſe, and feeling of this loue of God in our election, ſhould enkindle in vs a loue to him that hath ſo entirely loued, vs and therefore it cannot but be very iniurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to depriue people of the doctrine of election, which might bee as the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes to blow vp in them this little ſparke of heauenly loue to God.</p>
                  <p>But peraduenture ſome man may ſay,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                     </label> though the point of election may in ſome ſort be taught, yet reprobation (which is the paſsing by of many thouſands and the appointing them to eternall wrath) being a matter ſo full of horror (as indeed it is) were better concealed.</p>
                  <p>No,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                     </label> for God thinkes good to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh it in the ſcriptures, ſhall wee ſhut vp where God will open? Againe, what is the point of reprobation but an illuſtration of the greatnes of the grace of election, as contraries (wee
<pb facs="tcp:2933:8"/>know) laied one by an other are more perſpicuous: and how can we feele the ſweetnes of Gods loue in our owne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, till we ſee the terrour of his hate in the reiection of others? To this purpoſe <hi>Auguſt. tom. 4. li. 1. ad ſimp. q. 2.</hi> ſaith, that God ſheweth by the puniſhment of the one what hee giueth to the other.</p>
                  <p>Yea but this is a matter full of terrour.
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                     </label>
                     <note place="margin">Polan. in epiſt. libell. de Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt.</note> Hereto I anſwere as a learned diuine of our times doth: ſo that their harts are too te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, their eares too nice which cannot brooke this point. And if this were a good reaſon, it is a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying doctrine: <hi>Ergo,</hi> God may not be taught, then might we not preach of Gods iudgements, doomes day, the torments of hell; all which be matters full of terror. But to giue more full ſatisfaction in this point, the doctrine of reprobation is fearefull: to whom? either elect or reprobates, not to the elect, for God aſſureth them that they be not reiected: <hi>Ergo,</hi> to reprobates as <hi>Cain, Iudas,</hi> and the like, Now muſt we for their ſakes abſtaine from tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
<pb facs="tcp:2933:9"/>neceſſarie truthes?
<note place="margin">Iſaiah 8.14.</note> 
                     <hi>Iſaiah</hi> foretold long ſince that Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſhould be as a ſtone for theſe to ſtumble at, and as a rocke of offence for them to fall vpon, yet who will ſay that; <hi>Ergo,</hi> Chriſt ſhould not bee preachea? nay Chriſt muſt be taught though all the world ſhould be offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thereat.</p>
                  <p>Yet moreouer there be ſome (who being giuen to picke quarrels) ſticke not to auouch that we in our doctrine of reprobation, (wherein wee teach that God hath ordained ſome men to be damned) charge God with a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileſſe diſpoſition, which God forbid we ſhould once imagine to be in him, who is indeede euen mercy it ſelfe; wherefore I pray you giue leaue in a word or two to wipe away this ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
                  <p>Firſt it muſt bee remembred that we teach not that God doth ſimplie ordaine any man to hell fire, but thus we teach, that God hath decreed and purpoſed to glorifie his name in the due and deſerued damnation of ſome,
<pb facs="tcp:2933:9"/>for in mans Reprobation, God hath two actions: Firſt, he decrees to paſſe by ſome without ſhewing his eternall mercie vnto them, and onely to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his iuſtice vpon them; which thing hee may well doe without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trole, for he is tyed to none, then fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he decrees to inflict vpon ſome (when by themſelues they be fallen into ſinne) their iuſt and deſerued damnation. So that God decrees a man to hell, not ſimply and abſolutely without all reſpect to ſinne, but with a reference thereto. This point I take it, being well weighed, Gods iuſtice in reprobation is much cleered, and our doctrine freed from caſting the guilt of cruelty vpon the moſt high.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, I wiſh it might bee well conſidered how that in ſome caſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong our ſelues we giue liberty one to another to doe this or that as we will, and we think the action ſo done, both iuſt and lawfull; then ought we not much more to giue to the moſt wiſe and righteous God, a liberty in his actions to do euen as he will without
<pb facs="tcp:2933:10"/>all impute of cruelty or iniuſtice what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer?</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, we doe but require that in this caſe of reprobation, ſo much ſo ueraignty may be giuen to God euer men (which is moſt equall) as a ſilly and mortall man aſſumes to himſelfe ouer the creatures: we allow to a man ſo much power and libertie, as to kill a flie, or a worme at his will, to ſlay a ſheepe or an Oxe for his lawfull vſe and pleaſure, and all this without the leaſt tincture of cruelty, why then ſhould wee thinke much, to grant to God (the abſolute Lord of the ſpirits of all fleſh, and ſoueraigne King of the whole world) a liberty to appoint ſome men to bee paſſed by, and ſo to runne on to deſerued death, vpon his meere will and pleaſure?</p>
                  <p>Thus hauing ouermuch preſumed on your patience, leaſt I ſhould ſeeme iniurious in detaining you too long in this my rude and weariſome diſcourſe I here ſurceaſe, deſiring that what I haue here with a ſingle heart offered vnto your worſhips, may finde your
<pb facs="tcp:2933:10"/>moſt kinde and curteous acceptance.</p>
                  <p>The God of all mercy and goodnes who hath enriched your Citie with manifold bleſsings, and made it very famous for his Goſpell and good go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, perpetuate theſe his vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued fauours among you, with the further inlargement of your proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and grant that as hee hath made you his vice-gerents, and hath put his ſword into your hands, ſo hee would pleaſe to double his ſpirit of wiſedome, and courage vpon you all, that when you haue faithfully finiſhed your work for God, in a Zealous executing of iudgement and iuſtice here on earth, you may be rewarded with the life of glorie in the Citie of the moſt high. From <hi>Norwich,</hi> Nouemb. <hi>7. 1613.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Worſhips euer to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in the Lord,
<hi>Robert Gallard.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2933:11"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2933:11"/>
                  <head>TO THE GOD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LY READER, EN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of ſauing know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in heauenly <hi>things.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian Reader, ſo cenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious is this our age, as that nothing almoſt can paſſe without a nip. This I haue conſidered, and yet am thus bold (thou ſeeſt) to aduenture my ſelfe, as now I doe. I take it to be a want of Chriſtian courage to refuſe to attempt matters of publike good vpon a meere feare of being miſiudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: for what thing ſo wiſely done but ſome will taxe? Is it not the follie of moſt to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure things done by a falſe and crooked <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>wand? what through ignorance, curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, enuie, and ſiniſter affection, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon miſleading guides of mans iudgement, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> comes to paſſe that few things well done are well iudged, good oft times goeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of euill, and folly gets away wiſdomes praiſe. Wherefore ſetting at nought the vaine cenſorious humour of theſe our times, I haue yeelded at length to the earneſt entreaty, and importunate ſuite of ſome godly wiſe friends, for the ſetting out of theſe few Sermons, breaking through
<pb facs="tcp:2933:12"/>ſuch diſcouragements as were caſt in my way, hoping to bee iuſtified in what I haue done at leaſt by wiſedomes children.</p>
                  <p>The maine motiue that drew mee on to this buſineſſe, was not (God is my record) any outward by reſpect to my priuate ſelfe, but partly a deſire to continue the memory of a bleſſed man, but moſt of all the hope of winning ſome glory to God in his churches good, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> I profeſſe my ſelfe to reioyce, as in a thing moſt deere and precious vnto me, and therefore if I ſee that in thus doing I any whit aduance it, I haue this my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and alſo encouragement to future im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments in this kinde, and in the meane while ſhall bleſſe my God, that hath vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed to put my weake hand to theſe begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings.</p>
                  <p>Now for the matter ſet forth in this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle volume, it needs not my word of com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mendation, reade and thou ſhalt perceiue it ſpeaking ſufficiently for it ſelf. The points of doctrine which heere thou ſhalt meete with, are very needefull for thee both to know and practiſe, I wiſh thee a gainer in each reſpect, ſo ſhalt thou bee an happie man,</p>
                  <p>Some things there bee (I acknowledge) eſpecially in the Sermon of Predeſtination (as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith of a few things in <hi>Pauls</hi> Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles) hard to be vnderſtood;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pet.</hi> 23.16.</note> whereat when thou readeſt take heede thou doeſt not ſtumble and fall: take not occaſion to fall out with the doctrine of Gods decree, as many haue done, and ſplit the ſhips of their poore ſoules vpon that rocke which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> others.</p>
                  <p>If ought then thou meeteſt with of an
<pb facs="tcp:2933:12"/>higher ſtraine then thy ſhallow reach can attaine vnto, wrangle not, ſtrike not the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, for he intended thy good, blame not the matter, for that is Gods, nor manner of conueiance, for that is moſt perſpicuous for ſo deepe a myſterie: but if thou canſt not wade on with the Authour, ſtand ſtill and admire Gods wiſedome as <hi>Paul</hi> doth, ſaying,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.33.</note> 
                     <hi>O depth!</hi> or ſmite thy ſelfe, and blame that blind head of thine as being vnfit to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with ſuch high and heauenly ſtuffe, and to conceiue ſuch diuine truthes as thou art bound to know.</p>
                  <p>Now furthermore, whereas (good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) that arch enemie of Gods truth, Satan, hath offered much wrong to this doctrine of Gods decree, in thoſe manifold cauils which he hath hatched and broached from time to time by men of ſinne. Vouchſafe I pray you the patient peruſing of theſe few lines enſuing; wherein I haue a little en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauoured to anſwere the abſurd ſophiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call obiections which oft times wee heare breathed forth by black mouthed Atheiſts, for euen ſuch kinde of fooles (I hold) ſhould ſometimes be anſwered, leſt other happily ſhould bee entangled and periſh in their follie.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prou.</hi> 26.5.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, for that moſt vſual <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> common forme of reaſoning. ſe. If I bee predeſtinate to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, I am ſure to be ſaued let me do what I will; If I bee appointed to damnation, I am ſure to bee damned though I liue neuer ſo godly; for Gods decree changeth not, and therefore I will liue as I liſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Howbeit moſt deſperate and pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phane wretches (for ſuch they bee for the moſt part) doe take occaſion from Gods
<pb facs="tcp:2933:13"/>decree to reaſon in this ſort, yet wee muſt know that the occaſion is taken before it be giuen, for the doctrine of the vnchangea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble decree of God affords no ſuch conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion as beere is inferred. I am appointed to life or death vnchangeably, this is Gods truth: therefore it matters not how I liue. This is the diuels concluſion, not inferred by force of good reaſon (for in a Syllogiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call forme of reaſoning I am ſure no ſuch concluſion can be drawne) but framed and forged by the diuels art, and entertained for the moſt part in the braines of moſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute and diuelliſh men. But ſee we the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurditie of this conſequence, I am neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ordained to life or death: therefore I may liue as I liſt. This is a reaſoning from the putting too of the ſurpeme cauſe to a remouing of the inſtrumental, which are not oppoſite but ſubordinate one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<note place="margin">Ariſt. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> as Logicians doe ſpeake.</p>
                  <p>Againe, this kinde of reaſoning, ſc. I am appointed to eternall life, therefore I may liue as I liſt, vſing no meanes to attaine it, is as if a man ſhould reaſon thus, ſc. God hath ordained me to liue many yeeres, therefore what need I eate, or drinke, or ſleepe, or vſe any meanes, the reaſon is the ſame.</p>
                  <p>This one point muſt needs bee remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, that in Gods decree, the end, and the meanes tending to that end muſt goe hand in hand, in ſo much as, looke what God hath appointed to come to paſſe by meanes, thoſe meanes hee hath as neceſſarily ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to be vſed, as the end to bee archieued: yea, ſo inſeparably are the meanes and the euent knit together, as that if wee may ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a demad of the meanes, a deniall of
<pb facs="tcp:2933:13"/>the euent will neceſſarily be inferred there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon.</p>
                  <p>As for example. Act. 27. the Apoſtle ſaith, verſ. 24. that God had giuen him the liues of all thoſe that were in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhip; there was Gods decree: yet in the 31. verſ. the Apoſtle ſaith, that vnleſſe the ſhip-men did ſtay in the ſhip, they could not bee ſafe; heere is a deniall of the decreed meanes, inferring a deniall of the decreed euent. So then, I am ordained to eternall life; there is Gods de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree: if I ſhould not repent not beleeue, (which is impoſſible, God hauing decreed them likewiſe) ſurely I ſhould not be ſaued. The immutability therefore of Gods de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>creee, doth no whit fauour the neglect of meanes tending to eternall life. Wherefore as <hi>Hezekiah</hi> after hee knew Gods decree for fifteene yeeres to bee added to his daies, neglected not all meanes of life (for if hee had, he ſhould haue died) but applied phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke to his wound, are, dranke, and vſed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meanes of life; ſo hee that is ordained to eternall life, if hee would obtaine, muſt vſe the meanes, in repentance, faith, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, or elſe hee cannot looke to bee ſaued.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> Yea but now ſuppoſe a man bee appointed to damnation, may not that man ſo appointed reſolue with himſelfe to liue as he lift?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though this be granted to bee a true poſition, ſc. that a man appointed of God to wrath ſhall ſurely bee damned, yet no ſuch concluſion as this will enſue, ſc that that man may reſolue to liue as hee liſt. For firſt, there is no man liuing ſo acquainted with Gods decree (vnleſſe hee hath ſinned
<pb facs="tcp:2933:14"/>againſt the holy Ghoſt) as to know his own reiection: for how be it I finding by a liuely ſenſe a feeling of the ſpirit of ſanctification, my ſelfe in the eſtate of ſauing grace, may hereupon aſſure my ſelfe that I am elected, yet I may not, finding my ſelfe <hi>è contra,</hi> to bee in the eſtate of vnregeneracie, thereup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on conclude that I am a reprobate; for euen the elect are in the eſtate of ſinne before they be called. Againe, the Lord doth not ſeale vp to men their reprobation, as hee doth their election. What mad and hideous follie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is this for a man to reſolue to liue as a reprobate, before hee knowes whether he be ſo or no? As if a man ſhould condemne himſelfe, &amp; run poſt haſt to the place of exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, and put the rope about his owne necke, or vſe all meanes to make away him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, before hee know whether the ſentence of life or death bee paſt vpon in the Iudges breaſt. One dramme of good reaſon, much more of grace, would teach a man rather to argue thus: I know not whether the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of wrath be paſt in heauen againſt me or no; I will therefore reſolue to employ my ſelfe in all well doing, repenting of ſin, beleeuing in Chriſt, and yeelding obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to Gods Commandements, which is the only way to eternall life: by this meanes I ſhall make mine owne election ſure to my ſelfe, and ſo at length come to eternall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe. Thus wee vſe to reaſon in the like caſe. I know not whether it bee my lot to liue till the next yeere or no, I will eate, drinke, ſleepe, and vſe other meanes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed of God as the way to life, that ſo I may liue if it be poſſible. Suppoſe we thus, that a Iudge giue out to a companie of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactors
<pb facs="tcp:2933:14"/>before him in this ſort. I haue ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly with my ſelfe paſt a decree vpon you all, and that vnchangeably, wherein ſome of you are appointed to life, ſome to death; now they that bee mon of life ſhall ſurely come to me, and kneele downe before me, and ſue for pardon, the men of death ſhall not doe ſo; and this is the marke of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence: now looke to your ſelues. In this caſe ſhall not that man bewray his follie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all the reſt, that ſhall reſolue and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with himſelfe neuer to come &amp; kneele before the Iudge, becauſe the decree is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeablie paſt vpon him, either for life or death, which he knoweth not? ſhould bee not rather in all reaſon runne to the Iudge, and kneele before him, and ſue for pardon, that ſo he might aſſure himſelfe that hee is a man of life? Yes ſurely, euen thus it fareth in the caſe in hand; for God in his moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> councell hath made a decree <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> all men: wherein ſome are appointed to life, ſome to death vnchangeably: God hath further ſaid in his word, that the men ordained to life ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to him, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue which is the marke of their election, but the men of death ſhall not doe ſo: are not they then moſt ſeely and ſenſeleſſe fooles that ſhall vpon heareſay of an immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table decree paſt, whether for, or againſt them they know not, reſolue with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, neuer to turne to God, and beleeue, whereby as by moſt certaine ſignes they might proue to themſelues their owne ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction? Nay is not this a wilfull ſecluding of a mans ſelfe from the fauour of God, and a voluntarie branding of a mans ſelfe with the blacke marke of a reprobate before it
<pb facs="tcp:2933:15"/>be knowne whether God hath done ſo or no? Yes ſurely, for as the ſonnes of <hi>Eli</hi> did bewray their owne reiection by their obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate rebellion, for the text ſaith they did not hearken to the voyce of God,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.25.</note> becauſe the Lord would ſlay them (where their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate courſe in ſin is made a ſecret marke of their reprobation) euen ſo that man that reſolues with himſelfe to neglect God, and to runne on in ſinne, vpon this that God hath writ his deſtinie in heauen, doth as much as poſſibly he can ſeale vp to himſelfe his owne reprobation; and if hee thus both liue and dye, muſt needs be damned.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obiect.</hi> What then? If I going on in ſin bee damned, is not herein the vnreſiſtable will and pleaſure of God, which needs muſt ſtand, brought to paſſe?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yea it is, and that moſt iuſtly, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly through thine owne default, for thy ſinne brings by damnation as the due deſerued wages thereof: ſo iuſt is God as that he will inflict damnation vpon none that be inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and free from ſinne; God neuer did, neither will damne any man but for ſinne. And therefore, lay thine hand vpon thy mouth, and blame thy ſelfe for thine owne ruine;
<note place="margin">Hoſea. 13.</note> thy deſtruction is of thy ſelfe O Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, Hoſ. 13.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obiect.</hi> Yea, but had not God ordained me before to this end, I ſhould neuer by ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning brought damnation on my ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thou moſt ſaucie and molipert man, how dareſt thou take the dirt and mire of thine owne ſinne, and caſt it thus vpon the face of the moſt holy God? Thou ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, and by thy ſinne bringeſt vpon thy ſelf moſt iuſt damnation, and muſt God be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb facs="tcp:2933:15"/>for appointing thee to that thy deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued end? muſt this thy baſe and misbegot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ofſpring of ſin bee fathered vpon Gods moſt righteous decrees?</p>
                  <p>The concluſion then is this: A reprobate ſinneth, for his ſin hee periſheth, according to the neceſſarie and vnchangeble decree of God; yet man ſinneth of himſelf willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and is therefore condemned of God moſt iuſtly, and Gods moſt wiſe and iuſt decree no wit to be blamed.</p>
                  <p>I doubt not (good Reader) but that the reaſon of man is able to obiect yet much more, (for I ſee how our proud and thwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting nature is impatient of ſatisfaction in this point) but know, that as more might be obiected, ſo more might bee anſwered, and withal remember that mans reaſon (through the fall) is a corrupt thing, and hereupon will grow ſometimes very wilde and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, and therefore ſhe ſhould now and then receiue a checke for paſſing ſo beyond her bounds. I wiſh thee therfore when thou ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueſt in theſe and ſuch like diuine points, to caſt as it were a bridle vpon thy reaſon, and keepe her in from paſſing the liſts and limits of ſobrietie.</p>
                  <p>And becauſe I finde by experience how reſtleſſe and laſciuious a thing mans reaſon is, eſpecially in this point of Gods decree, as alſo now armed and furniſhed with the di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueliſh art of wrangling. I thinke meete ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther here to ſtint my ſpeech, then to admit of any further diſcourſe. As for ſuch as will not admit of that reaſonable ſatisfaction, which I hope I haue giuen, but will aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture through the pride of their wits to chop Logick with their Maker, and to call him to
<pb facs="tcp:2933:16"/>his reaſons, who is bound to render his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to none,
<note n="*" place="margin">God is <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> I pray God to make them more ſober-minded, and doe wiſh them to conſider with all humilitie that ſaying of the Apoſtle, Rom. 9.19. <hi>O man who art thou that diſputeſt with God? ſhall the thing formed ſay to him that formed it, why haſt thou made me thus? hath not the potter power ouer the clay of the ſame lumpe to make one veſſell vnto honour, and another vnto diſhonour?</hi> This place well pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred in the ſpirit of humilitie, would ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently ſerue to ſtop our mouthes that wee ſhould not haue one word to ſpeake, and to ſet our haughtie reaſon at a <hi>non plus,</hi> ſo as it ſhould not haue a thought to thinke againſt that diſpoſall which God hath made of the ſoules of men in his decree, ſeeing hee is an abſolute and a ſoueraigne Lord of the ſpirits of all fleſh, and therfore may deale with men according to his will, imparting or withhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his mercie euen as he pleaſeth, and that without check or controle from any: for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, what are wee but the creatures of God, the meere workmanſhip of his hands? farre more in his power then the clay in the pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, for the clay is Gods creature, not the potters, and will haue a being in ſpight of the potter: whereas wee are continually in Gods power and at his meere curteſie for our very being.</p>
                  <p>Thus gentle Reader, for the preuention of ſcandall, I thought meete to endeuour the remouall of ſuch ſtumbling blockes, as the doctrine of Gods decree, or this treatiſe in particular through Satans malice, might ſeeme to caſt in thy way; If I haue giuen thee ſatisfaction (which is hard to doe in ſuch knottie doubts) I haue my wiſh; if not,
<pb facs="tcp:2933:16"/>yet let our poore endeuour bee taken in good worth. I haue been (I acknowledge) ouer longſome and tedious, paſſing ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what the limits of an Epiſtle: but the weight of the matter, and difficultie of the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which can hardly bee handled both briefly and plainly, will be, I hope, my ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient apologie with men of vnderſtanding, and therefore I ſpare to craue pardon herein.</p>
                  <p>As for thoſe other Sermons about the vnchangeable eſtate of Gods childe, <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme,</hi> and <hi>the feare of God,</hi> I aduiſe thee to caſt thine eye moſt what on them, as being more eaſie to conceiue, &amp;, as I take it, more fit for thine vſe, and moſt behooffull for thy learning: yet leſt I ſhould ſeeme too buſie in giuing aduice I leaue thee to thine owne diſcretion. Thou knoweſt how the Bee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king her choice in a garden of flowers, there tarieth longeſt where ſhee findeth moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; ſo thou in reading this booke make thy choice, and there ſtay moſt where thou ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt that which is moſt ſit for thine vſe.</p>
                  <p>Thus (curteous Reader) as one mindfull and deſirous of thy good, I haue been bold, according to my poore skill, to counſel thee for the beſt: I intend, God knoweth, thy ſoules welfare in Chriſt Ieſus, and would much reioyce in a bleſſed inlargement of his grace in thine heart: yea ſurely, if any thing in this booke ſhall further the ſame, thrice happie ſhall I iudge my ſelfe to be in hauing an hand to procure thee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
                  <p>And now I leaue thee to the further view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of what I haue here laid before thine eye, be not (I pray thee) left handed in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing
<pb facs="tcp:2933:17"/>what I giue thee with the right. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe what here thou findeſt to thy beſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage: If ought thou gaineſt, giue God the glorie, and me thy good word for my good will.</p>
                  <p>That God that wet the fleece of <hi>Ged<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> with his owne dew,
<note place="margin">Iudg. 6.38.</note> powre downe from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the dew of his bleſſing vpon thy rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and repleniſh thine heart with ſuch a plentifull meaſure of his grace, that liuing here in righteouſnes and true holines, may hereafter haue thy part in that glorie and happineſſe, that ſhall be reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led at the comming of our Lord Ieſus. <hi>Norwich,</hi> Nouember 14. 1613.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Thine in Chriſt Ieſus
Robert Gallard.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2933:17"/>
                  <head>A SERMON, WHEREIN IS OPE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NED THE MANNER OF Gods decree concerning Election and Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>1. THESS. 5.9.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>For God hath not appointed vs vnto wrath, but to the obtaining of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by the meanes of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the three firſt verſes of this Chapter the Apoſtle continueth in the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the laſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which hee had propounded in the latter end of the former: wherein he ſignifieth vnto the Theſſalonians, that the time of the ſecond comming of Chriſt ſhould bee ſudden and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne vnto all, eſpecially vnto the wicked, whom it ſhall ouertake vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares and vnprouided. Which thing he declareth by the example of the theefe, who vpon the night, when men leaſt thinke of it, breaketh vp
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2933:18"/>another mans houſe: and of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man with childe, whoſe trauell comes vpon her vnexpected. In the 4. and 5. verſes hee comforteth them againſt the terror of this ſudden comming of the Lord, intimating vnto them that there was no cauſe why they ſhould greatly ſtand in feare of it, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring they were not in darkneſſe and ignorance, but enlightened with the knowledge of the truth, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were not the children of the darkneſſe and of the night, but of the light and of the day: whereupon in the 6.7. and 8. verſes hee diſſwadeth them from ſecuritie, and perſwadeth them vnto vigilancie and ſobrietie; And leſt the enemie by his ſubtiltie ſhould at any time circumuent them, hee willeth them alwaies to bee in a readines, furniſhed, prepared and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parelled with the ſpirituall armour of Chriſtian ſouldiers, <hi>viz,</hi> faith, loue, and hope. This exhortation (that it might take the better place) he enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth it by a reaſon taken from the end, whereunto the Theſſalonians in the decree and counſell of God were appointed, to wit, eternall happineſſe, the which is propounded in a diſcreet axiome on this manner: <hi>God hath not
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2933:18"/>appointed vs vnto wrath, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The words in themſelues containe a deſcription of the decree of Gods election. Firſt from the Author, that is, God. Secondly from the obiect, that is, <hi>Paul</hi> and the elect Theſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians. Thirdly from the nature, that is, an appointment or ordaining of them to the obtaining of ſaluation. Fourthly, from the principall meanes of execution, that is, the mediation of Ieſus Chriſt. Laſtly, it is amplified by the contrarie, that is, the decree of Reprobation, which is alſo deſcribed to be the appointment of ſome vnto wrath.</p>
                  <p>Touching the meaning of the words, they are very plaine, I ſhall not neede to ſpend much time in the vnfolding of them. For whereas the Apoſtle ſaith that God hath not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, the meaning is, God in his eternall and vnchangeable counſell and decree hath not appointed to manifeſt and declare his wrath (for ſo by a <hi>metonimie</hi> of the ſubiect (I take it) wee are to expound the words) in our iuſt and deſerued condemnation, but to make knowne the riches of his mercies in our free and gracious ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and that by the meanes and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2933:19"/>for the merit of Ieſus Chriſt. This is the ſimple meaning of the words. On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one doubt may be here made, how the Apoſtle came to the knowledge of this decree, eſpecially touching the Theſſalonians: but the anſwer is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die; that hee ſpeaketh of them accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the iudgement of charity, and not of certainty, the reaſon hereof is plaine, becauſe diuers of the Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians afterward fell wholly away from the faith and religion of Chriſt they did profeſſe: ſo that in the end they ceaſed to be a Church.</p>
                  <p>Now then that we ſee in ſome part the order and meaning of the words, let vs in the next place come to the vſe of doctrine and edification which they doe naturally affoord.</p>
                  <p>The firſt doctrine is generall out of the whole text, to wit, that there is a difference and diſiunction of men in the decree and counſell of God, ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſome reprobate, ſome appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſaluation, ſome vnto wrath: this point is cleere and euident out of this text, though there were no other ſcripture to confirme the ſame; where the Apoſtle ſorts all men into two or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders or rankes, ſome whereof are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed vnto wrath, out of which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2933:19"/>number hee exempts himſelfe and the elect Theſſalonians; and ſome to the attaining of ſaluation, in which num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber hee rangeth himſelfe with them. And leſt any man ſhould doubt of the ſignification of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and of the ſenſe of it in this place, let him reade Iohn 15.16. and Acts 13.47. where the ſame word is vſed in the ſame ſignification. But for the fuller and more ſufficient confirmation of this point, compare the 2. Tim. 2.19. with Matth. 7.23. where it is affirmed of ſome, <hi>The Lord knowes who are his:</hi> which is the ſeale of their Election, and of others our Sauiour Chriſt ſhall pronounce at the day of iudgement, <hi>I neuer knew you,</hi> that is, acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged you for mine. Rom. 9.22. there are veſſels of mercie prepared vnto glorie, and veſſels of wrath fitted to deſtruction. 2. Tim. 2.20. there bee veſſels of honour, and veſſels of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour. Examples alſo heereof are propounded in <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Eſan,</hi> Rom. 9.13. <hi>Iacob haue I loued,</hi> that is, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to loue with an eternall loue, but <hi>Eſau haue I hated,</hi> that is, purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to hate with an eternall hatred.</p>
                  <p>But againſt this cleere and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued expoſition many exceptions are
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2933:20"/>made. Firſt it is alleaged that by <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> wee are not to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand their particular perſons, but their poſteritie, <hi>viz.</hi> two natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which deſcended from them of the Iſraelites and Idumeans, for ſo the diuine oracle anſwereth <hi>Rebecca.</hi> Geneſis 25.33. <hi>Two nations are in thy wombe, and the elder ſhall ſerue the younger:</hi> which thing was neuer accompliſhed in the daies of <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> but rather of the twaine <hi>Iacob</hi> was in feare and ſubiection to <hi>Eſau,</hi> then contrariwiſe. But the text will not tolerate this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, for it is abſurd to ſay that two nations were conceiued at once, and did ſtriue together in the wombe of <hi>Rebecca,</hi> vnleſſe we conſider them as they were comprehended vnder their heads, to wit, the perſons of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> and <hi>Eſau.</hi> And whereas it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied that <hi>Eſau</hi> in perſon was neuer ſeruant vnto <hi>Iacob,</hi> the anſwere is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, that <hi>Iacobs</hi> preeminence and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges were not ſo much in tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall as in ſpirituall things, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore proportionally <hi>Eſau</hi> was deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the condition of a ſeruant in reſpect of his younger brother, not ſo much in his outward eſtate, as in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the couenant made with his
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2933:20"/>anceſtors, from which hee was iuſtlie for his prophanenes and vnthankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes debarred. Againe, though it were granted that by <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> two nations and not two perſons were vnderſtood, yet all comes to one head: for the receiuing of the nation of the Iſraelites into the couenant, and the excluding of the Edomites, both deſcending of <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> ſeeme as well to proue Gods eternall Election and Reprobation, as the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing and reiecting of particular men.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, others alleage and ſay, that by loue and hatred we are not to vnderſtand the eternal decree of God in Election and Reprobation, but temporall bleſſings, wherein <hi>Iacob</hi> was preferred before <hi>Eſau,</hi> eſpecially that to him and his poſteritie was vouchſafed the right and poſſeſſion of the land of Canaan, which was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied to his elder brother. <hi>Anſw.</hi> If this were the meaning of the text, then the Apoſtle ſhould bee accuſed of vnskilfulnes, in alleaging theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples to proue the reiection of the Iewes from the Couenant, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they ſhould bee altogether im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent: for though it were gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2933:21"/>there were a difference betweene man and man in reſpect of earthlie bleſſings, yet hereof it followeth not that there ſhould bee the ſame diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in things concerning the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen. Againe, the land of Canaan was not onely an earthly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance (we are not ſo carnally to conceiue of it) but a pledge and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure to our forefathers of a farre bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter inheritance in heauen: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the excluding of <hi>Eſau</hi> from the land of Canaan, was a ſigne that hee was excluded from the couenant of grace and the right of eternall life.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, it is obiected that to admit this expoſition makes <hi>Iſmael</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau</hi> damned perſons, which is a hard cenſure. <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is the ſafeſt to leane ſecret iudgements touching particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular perſons vnto God: but whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer their ſtate is before God, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle hath fitly in their two perſons both deſcending from <hi>Abraham,</hi> and both circumciſed, ſet forth examples of ſuch as for all their outward pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiues are indeed barred from the couenant of life euerlaſting before God. Againe, the oppoſition made by <hi>Paul</hi> requires that the contrarie to that which is ſpoken of <hi>Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2933:21"/>
                     <hi>Iacob,</hi> ſhould bee affirmed of <hi>Iſmael</hi> and <hi>Eſau.</hi> Neither is there a word in Scriptures which argues in them any diſpoſition of men ordained to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life: <hi>Iſmael</hi> is noted with the brand of a mocker, and <hi>Eſau</hi> of a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane perſon. And leſt any man ſhould think, that this doctrine is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of the teſtimony of the Church and of men, I referre them to <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> in his booke <hi>de ciuit. Dei, lib.</hi> 15. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. and to his <hi>Enchirid. ad Lauren. cap.</hi> 100. and to <hi>Thom. part.</hi> 1. <hi>qu.</hi> 23. <hi>art.</hi> 1. I may not waſte the time in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing the teſtimonies at large. And thus much of the generall doctrine, the vſe followeth which is two-fold, partly in confutation of error, partly in inſtruction vnto godlineſſe.</p>
                  <p>Touching confutation it ſerueth firſt of all to ouerthrow the error of ſome Diuines, that terme themſelues <hi>Lutherans,</hi> and Imitators of <hi>Caſtellio,</hi> who hold and teach, and in their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings publiſh and maintaine that God for his part hath caſt lots of no man, but hath willed and decreed to ſaue all and euery particular man without exception of any, ſo be it they wil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue. But this confuſed and vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall decree falleth to the ground, if
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2933:22"/>God hath ſorted and diſtinguiſhed men in his eternall counſell, as wee haue before demonſtratiuely proued out of Scriptures. But that the truth in this point may bee more euident, and error more manifeſtly detected, againſt this indiſtinct and generall decree many reaſons may bee allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, ſauing grace is not giuen to all, as faith, hope, loue, repentance, perſeuerance, which are the meanes of ſaluation, therefore all are not ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to eternall life: the ground of this reaſon is infallible, to wit, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer are ordained to the end are ordained to the meanes, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly and directly ſerue to the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhing of the ſame end: ſo much the word predeſtination in Latin ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth, <hi>viz.</hi> the appointing of ſuch an end, which is not but by ſet and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed meanes thereunto ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, as by certaine ſteps and degrees, atchieued. And <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 8.30. hath ſo linked and knit theſe things toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that it is impoſſible to ſeuer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but it muſt needs be that whoſoeuer are predeſtinate, they are alſo called, iuſtified, and ſhall be glorified. But it will be replied, that ſufficiencie of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2933:22"/>grace is giuen to all, though it be not effectual in all, &amp; that through the default of the receiuers. <hi>Anſw.</hi> This diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the matter of grace is frinolous and abſurd, whatſoeuer <hi>Bellarmine</hi> or any other can ſay to the contrary. The reaſon hereof is plaine: for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> grace be ſufficient vnto ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fiue things are required. Firſt, the col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating or donation of grace. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, power and abilitie to receiue the grace giuen, which is done by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther grace. Thirdly, the retaining or keeping of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace receiued. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the vſing of the grace receiued and kept. Fifthly, the perſeuerance in it, or the conſtant keeping and vſing of the grace giuen and receiued, whereof if any bee wanting, it is not ſufficient, if all be there it muſt needs be effectuall, vnleſſe we will ſay, that he that continueth to the end in faith and obedience ſhall not bee ſaued, contrary to the expreſſe text of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Againe, theſe are ſo coupled and combined together, that whoſoeuer hath the firſt grace truly and indeed, hee muſt needes haue the ſecond, to wit, perſeuerance, otherwiſe hee hath not true ſauing grace, but a ſhadow of it, the perſeuerance being a part of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2933:23"/>the truth of grace, 1. Ioh. 2.19. ſo as men liuing in the Church, are then knowne to be counterfeits and hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites when they doe not perſeuere. And if perſeuerance doth not alwaies accompanie true ſauing grace, what will be the difference and preferment of the ſtate of Redemption, before the ſtate of Creation? <hi>Adam</hi> before the fall in his innocencie had indeede to can that he would, but hee had not to will that he could, but whoſoeuer are in Chriſt, as all are that haue receiued ſauing grace, they haue in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure both <hi>poſſe &amp; velle,</hi> ſo as it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible they ſhould either totally fall, or finally periſh. Mans ſaluation being put into his owne hands, was loſt becauſe hee was not confirmed with new grace in the act of tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but being now committed to the cuſtodie of Chriſt it is ſafe &amp; ſure, he hauing ouercome Satan and al the powers of hell, by ſubtiltie and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence whereof it might haue bin en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered.</p>
                  <p>To make this plaine by a familiar compariſon vſed by
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Loc. com. pag.</hi> 464.</note> 
                     <hi>Peter Martyr.</hi> Suppoſe there were a great weight of timber or ſtone to be moued, if a man ſhall put to ſo much force as is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2933:23"/>that is, ſo much as may preuaile againſt the greatnes of the mole, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion muſt neceſſarily follow: in like manner, God being to moue the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie and wicked hearts of men, if hee ſhall of his mercie infuſe but ſo much grace as is ſufficient, that is, ſo much as will counteruaile the hardnes and prauitie of them, it cannot be auoided but they muſt bee moued and molli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and that not by any viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion, but by a moſt effectuall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion.</p>
                  <p>As for the diſtinction of ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and efficacie, and the difference in
<note n="*" place="margin">An example of the naturall agent. The Sunne hath ſufficiencie to enlighten all men, but not efficacie in the blinde.</note> naturall and voluntarie agents, it is to bee acknowledged, and hath his place in things wherein man by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath power and freedome of will to doe or not to doe: for example, to talke, to goe, to ſit, or to vſe any like poſition of the body, a man may haue the ſufficiencie, that is, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and yet not the efficacie, that is, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>: and why? becauſe hee will not, and hee hath power to ſtay the action of the
<note n="*" place="margin">Motiue.</note> naturall facultie; but in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters concerning the kingdom of God the caſe is farre otherwiſe: for who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer hath ſufficient grace, by it his will is ſo corrected and rectified, that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2933:24"/>he effectually willeth his owne ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And for men to imagine that a man doth repell true ſufficient grace though in neuer ſo ſmall meaſure, it is to make man
<note n="*" place="margin">Verum eſt nos fruſtra velle niſi Deus miſerea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur: at quis dix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erit deum fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra miſereri ſi nos nolimus.</note> ſtronger then God. Neither doth the place, Acts 7.51. any whit at al patronage this error, where <hi>Stephen</hi> vpbraideth the ſtiffe-necked. Iewes with this, that they had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies reſiſted the holy Ghoſt, for he ſpeaketh not of the inward powerfull worke of the holy Ghoſt in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; but of his outward voyce in the externall miniſterie of the word, Nor that other place, Matth. 23.37. <hi>I would, but ye would not:</hi> for there our Sauiour Chriſt ſpeaketh not as hee was God equall with his Father, for then who could haue reſiſted his wil? but as man, or rather as miniſter of Circumciſion, as the Apoſtle termeth him, Rom. 15.8. whoſe office was to will and procure by all meanes the ſaluation of men, that herein alſo hee might be an example to the Miniſters of the new Teſtament, who were to ſucceed him, whoſe dutie and care is alſo to will and to further the ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all. But notwithſtanding all this, it is thought by ſome both Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts and Proteſtants Diuines, that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2933:24"/>grace may bee giuen to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate, and to credit and authorize this opinion, it is fathered vpon <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,</hi> and affirmed to be his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and to this end two places are alleaged, one out of the 8. chapter <hi>de corrupt. &amp; gratia:</hi> the other out of the 13. chapter of the ſame booke. <hi>Anſ.</hi> Albeit as our late learned Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der anſwered vnto <hi>Duraeus: Malo tecum de poſſeſſione ſcripturaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, quam patrum contendere:</hi> yet ſomewhat I haue thought good to ſay, both to deliuer <hi>Auguſtine</hi> from ſuſpition of this error, and alſo for the fuller ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of the truth in this point. Concerning the firſt place: <hi>Miran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, multum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> mirandum, &amp;c.</hi> in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect thus much. It is greatly to bee wondred at, that certaine ſonnes of God, whom hee hath regenerated in Chriſt, and to whom hee hath giuen faith, hope, loue, &amp;c. ſhould notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding fall away and in the end pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh. <hi>Anſ.</hi> This needs not to trouble any man, that wil but peruſe the chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter following, wherein <hi>Auguſtine</hi> doth ſufficiently expound his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. In the beginning of the chapter hee diſtinguiſheth of the ſonnes of God: ſome are ſonnes of God vnto
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2933:25"/>God, or before God, that is, truly and indeed; and ſome are ſonnes of God vnto men, or in mans iudgement, that is, counterfeit ſonnes, which, as hee ſaith afterward, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were ſons, were no ſonnes, that is, as himſelf ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth, euen then when they were <hi>ſub nomine &amp; profeſſione filiorum Dei,</hi> were no ſonnes of God indeed. And looke how they are called ſonnes, ſo in the ſame ſenſe they are ſaid to bee regenerate, and to haue faith, hope and loue, <hi>viz.</hi> in the iudgement of men, and <hi>quoad praeſentem iuſtitiam,</hi> as he alſo noteth. But <hi>Bellarmine</hi> fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding no ſure hold in this place, very cunningly paſſeth it ouer, leſt by oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of it a man being led to the 9. chapter ſhould ſee <hi>Auguſtins</hi> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning more fully, and ſo be able to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere them both, and therefore in his 3. Tome, 3. booke, <hi>de Iuſtif. cap.</hi> 14. he alleageth the latter, wherein there ſeemeth to be more colour &amp; proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, then in the former. The effect of it is this: <hi>Credendum, &amp;c.</hi> We are to beleeue that certaine ſonnes of perdition, which begin to liue in the faith which worketh by loue, ſhall notwithſtanding before they goe out of this life wholly fall away and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2933:25"/>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> The meaning of <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> is this, that reprobates liuing in the Church may haue certaine begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and degrees vnto iuſtifying faith, as knowledge of the Goſpell and aſſent thereunto, yea and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed perſwaſion that many hereby are iuſtified and ſhall bee ſaued, and falſely alſo perſwade themſelues of their own ſaluation, whereupon they ioy and take pleaſure in their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and profeſſion, and are zealous for the Lord of Hoaſts as <hi>Iehu</hi> was, and doe reuerence the Miniſters as <hi>Herod</hi> did <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> and diſlike prophane perſons, and ſuch as are contemners of the word, and diſorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in their liues, and yet for all that are not ſound at the heart, the word of God hauing no thorow rooting in them, but (like vnto the ſtony ground wherein the ſeede, for want of ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient rooting, at the heate of the Sun is parched and withered away) in the time of temptation they wholly fall away. And that <hi>Auguſtine</hi> neuer meant that true ſauing faith could e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer faile, and therefore could neuer befall the reprobate, it is manifeſt out of his 106. Tract vpon <hi>Iohn:</hi> where, vpon the 17. chapt. verſe 8. <hi>Et cogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerurt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2933:26"/>vere &amp; crediderunt,</hi> hee hath theſe words: <hi>Crediderunt</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>ſubaudiendum vere, quomodo creden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſt: id eſt, inconcuſſe, firme, ſtabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter, fortiter, non iam in propria redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turi, &amp; Chriſtum relicturi.</hi> Now then if by <hi>Auguſtins</hi> iudgement true faith whereſoeuer it bee, is perpetuall, then it followeth that it cannot bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated vnto the reprobate, for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo it ſhould remaine with them for euer, and aduance them to eternal life. But whatſoeuer <hi>Auguſtins</hi> iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was, he was but a man, no Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet nor Apoſtle, and therefore not priuiledged from errour, touching whom, though euer to be reuerenced in the Church, we may ſay as himſelf ſaid of <hi>Cyprian,</hi> when as the Donatiſts alleaged his authoritie againſt him: Whatſoeuer (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> hath ſaid agreeable to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, I receiue it with his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Quicquid non congruit, cum eius pace, respuo.</hi> Let vs therefore come to the Scriptures, one ſentence whereof ought to be of greater price and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue with vs, and with greater reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and admiration to be receiued of vs, then tenne thouſand ſentences of humane writings, out of which the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2933:26"/>euidence of this point may moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be concluded. Acts 13.48. <hi>So many as were ordained to eternall life beleeued.</hi> Where the reſtraint is to be obſerued, the Apoſtle doth not make faith common to all, but to the elect onely, excluding (as it is manifeſt to any indifferent reader) all others which were not ordained to life. And leſt any man might doubt of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality &amp; reciprocation of the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, that is, faith and election, let him reade Tit. 1.1. where the Apoſtle ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of a faith proper to the elect, which the article plainly declareth, put there for diſtinction ſake; noting that there is a faith indeed in repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, to wit, a temporarie, or hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call faith, but not the faith of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, <hi>viz.</hi> ſauing and iuſtifying faith, the which whoſoeuer hath, hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently eternall life, Ioh. 3.36. not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in a blind and coniecturall hope, as the Papiſts ſay, but in a certaine and infallible perſwaſion grounded vpon the word and promiſe of God, and in ſuch a hope as diſappointeth not, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther maketh aſhamed, neither that only but in preſent poſſeſſion, if wee regard the beginnings of it: for there are three degrees of eternall life; the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2933:27"/>firſt is in this life, in faith and regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; the ſecond in the end of this life in the totall aboliſhment of ſinne, which is the accompliſhment of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification; the third is after this life, at the reſurrection in the fulnes of glory, wherewith both ſoule and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die ſhall bee repleniſhed for euer: wherfore the firſt degree or entrance into this life is made ſo ſoone as a man beginneth to beleeue. Further, in the ſame chapter, verſ. 18. hee that beleeueth (ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt) is not condemned, neither euer ſhall be, as it appeareth, Ioh. 5.24. but hath alreadie paſſed from death vnto life: and Rom. 8.1. There is no condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to them that by faith are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted into Chriſt: &amp; leſt any ſhould doubt of their perſeuerance, hee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth by way of deſcription, that they are ſuch as walke not according to the fleſh, but according to the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</p>
                  <p>Further, that true faith is an infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible note of election, it is manifeſt, 2. Tim. 2.21. whoſoeuer purgeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from theſe hee ſhall be a veſſell vnto honour. Whence I reaſon thus:
<note n="*" place="margin">The ſyllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme at large may thus be framed: If ſanctificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be a ſure mark of election, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaith is ſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable fruit of faith: But ſanctification is a ſure marke of election: Therefore, &amp;c.</note> Sanctification is a ſure marke of ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; now ſanctification is a fruit of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2933:27"/>faith, for that alone purifieth the hart, Acts 15. <hi>Ergo.</hi> And indeede Ioh. 14.16.17. our Sauiour Chriſt denieth that the world, that is, reprobates, can receiue the ſpirit of regeneration, which is the comforter and leader in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all truth: and <hi>Paul,</hi> 2. Cor. 13.5. excepteth the reprobates from the number of ſuch as haue Ieſus Chriſt dwelling in their hearts by faith. By al which it is more then manifeſt that true ſauing grace is neuer communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to the reprobate.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, if this doctrine might ſtand, three notable abſurdities in Diuinitie would neceſſarilie follow vpon it. Firſt, that reprobates in their perſons and actions ſhall ſometimes pleaſe God, <hi>viz.</hi> when they haue faith, and worke from faith; for faith is that, that makes both perſon and action accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to God: but how can this ſtand with that of our Sauiour Chriſt? Matth. 7.23. who ſhall pronounce at the day of iudgement of them that were otherwiſe adorned with moſt rare and ſingular gifts and graces of God; I neuer knew you, at no time I approued you either in your perſons or works, I neuer acknowledged you for mine: which hee would not, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2933:28"/>could ſay, if euer they had been indued with true faith, for at that time at the leaſt he muſt needes haue acknowledged them to be his.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, the certaintie of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion falleth flat to the ground, for the which wee contend ſo much with the Papiſts, for what other <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> or <hi>medium</hi> is there, wherby to perſwade the conſcience of the certaintie of ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction beſides faith; which if it be a common grace to the reprobate with the Elect, then no <hi>certitudo fidei,</hi> for a man may beleeue the pardon of a ſin, and yet for all that be a reprobate.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, the very reprobate ones ſhall be true members of Chriſt, and of the Catholike Church, which is meere Poperie, and the thing that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and the Papiſts labour to eſtabliſh.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, the very word Election ouerturneth this deuice of an vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall decree, for in euery choice there is a taking of ſome, and a refuſall of other ſome, and he that electeth can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaid to take all but ſome only. <hi>Obiect.</hi> To elect, is to loue: but God loueth all his creatures, and therefore chuſeth all. <hi>Anſw.</hi> To elect is not to loue, but to deſtinate and appoint to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2933:28"/>an eternall loue. Againe, God loues not all with an equall loue, hee is ſaid to loue all in that hee willeth good vnto all, but not the good of eternall life. Thus <hi>Thomas</hi> anſwereth, <hi>part.</hi> 1. <hi>qu.</hi> 23. <hi>art.</hi> 3.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, wee ſee by the euent that all come not to eternall life, but ſome only; how then can we imagine that the finall eſtate of a man in ſaluation and damnation ſhould come to paſſe without the decree of God? Ioh. 17.2.11. our Sauiour Chriſt giueth eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life to them alone that were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him of the Father, that is, thoſe that were elected: now if all had bin elected, why did he not ſpeake gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, that he gaue eternall life to all, but reſtraineth it to thoſe that were giuen him of the Father. But here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception will be made; though Gods decree bee vniuerſall, yet conceiued with a condition, which when men doe not obſerue, no maruell though they miſcarrie and come not to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life. <hi>Anſw.</hi> This conditionall decree is a fooliſh dreame of mans braine, and carrieth with it many groſſe abſurdities. Firſt, the Scripture hath not ſpoken a word of it, but whenſoeuer it mentioneth the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2933:29"/>it ſimply and categorically pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth it, as Rom. 9 and Ephe. 1.4. <hi>He hath choſen vs before the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the world.</hi> It will be replied, the Goſpell is propounded with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and that is nothing elſe but Gods predeſtination reuealed. <hi>Anſ.</hi> Albeit I confeſſe that the Goſpell doth in ſome part reueale the decree of God, yet it followeth not, that it is to bee confounded with it; and that they are things diſtinct one from an other may appeare by theſe differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, predeſtination being as it is commonly vſed in Scriptures, and in the writings of Diuines referred to the Elect, is that wherein God deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineth what he will doe touching vs or in vs, and hereupon the definition of <hi>Auguſtine</hi> is commonly receiued. It is the preparation of the bleſſing of God, wherby they are deliuered, that are deliuered: But the Goſpell is that wherein hee determineth by dutie what we are to doe vnto him.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, in predeſtination hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fineth both the materiall and formall number (as the Schoolemen ſpeake) that is, who and how many they are that ſhall be ſaued, which number can
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2933:29"/>neither be augmented, diminiſhed, or altered: whereupon our Sauiour Chriſt, Iohn 13.18. <hi>I know</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>whom I haue choſen.</hi> In the Goſpell he deſcribeth them by their qualities wherewith they are to be endued, to wit, faith and repentance.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, predeſtination is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree it ſelfe: the Goſpell an outward meanes of execution, whereupon the Goſpell may be conceiued with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, though the decree bee moſt ſimple and abſolute, and therefore hath the Goſpell a condition annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed both in reſpect of the godly, that they might bee aſſured of their ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, obſeruing the condition, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of the wicked, that they neglecting it might be the more inexcuſable, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially they being not ignorant that the Lord required it at their hands.</p>
                  <p>Againe, many inconueniences doe follow of this conditionall decree: for firſt if God hath decreed the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of men with condition, then this condition muſt depend either vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the will of the Creator, or the will of the creature; if vpon his own will, the tenour of the decree ſhall be this: God hath decreed or willed to ſaue all men if he will, which is abſurd to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2933:30"/>common reaſon: if vpon mans will, then the condition is either poſſible or impoſſible, if poſſible either vnto nature or vnto grace: not vnto na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for that is Pelagianiſme; not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to grace, for thereof followes three notable abſurdities. Firſt, that grace is communicated to all, and to euery particular man. Secondly, that by vertue of this grace euery man hath a flexible will like vnto <hi>Adam,</hi> ſo as hee may will his ſaluation, or nill it. Thirdly (which followeth of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer) that he may reſiſt and reiect the ſauing grace of God, which in no wiſe is to be admitted, as in part wee haue proued before.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, this conditionall decree implieth in it a contradiction, for the condition muſt needes be either euill or good: no man will affirme that God decreeth any thing vpon an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill condition, and if it bee good, it is an effect of predeſtination &amp; a means of ſaluation, vnto which a man is as well predeſtinate, as vnto the end: for example, wee are predeſtinate, not if we doe beleeue, but that we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, and conſequently bee ſaued: now for a man to bee predeſtinate, if he doe beleeue, is to bee predeſtinate
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2933:30"/>to the end, and not to the meanes, that is, to be predeſtinate, and not to be predeſtinate: for that word ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth to be predeſtinate vnto an end, which wee come vnto by ſet and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed meanes.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, it faſtneth vpon God ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie indignities; as firſt that it ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerteth the order of nature, ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding moſt impiouſly and indignely the will of the Creator, which is the firſt and ſupreme cauſe of al vpon the will of the creature, againſt a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon rule receiued in Schooles, <hi>Actus primae cauſae ordinat actum ſecundae:</hi> which is nothing elſe but to make man the Lord and Emperour, &amp; God to bee his vnderling. Secondly, it aſcribes vnto God either impendence or want of knowledge, as that hee is ignorant of the euents of things, or elſe impotencie and want of power, that he is not able to effect, what hee hath willed and decreed; no other reaſon can bee deuiſed of the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall decree: for we ſee among men that they are conſtrained to annexe conditions to their decrees, either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they know not how things will befall out, and ſo might be deceiued, or elſe doe want power to effect that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2933:31"/>which they would: but if they might haue their choice they would decree al things abſolutely; far be it therfore fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs to charge God with that, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we would diſburthen our ſelues.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, it makes the decree of predeſtination to be vncertaine; for to decree a thing conditionally, is to decree vncertainly, conſidering that the conditionall propoſition doth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme or determine nothing certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, nay it is as though God had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed nothing at all concerning man, eſpecially when as the thing deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined is in the power of mans will, and in reſpect of God, the decree may come to paſſe, or not come to paſſe.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, if God haue decreed to ſaue all, if they doe beleeue, by like pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of reaſon he may bee ſaid to haue decreed to refuſe and condemne all, ſo bee it they doe not beleeue: for by as good reaſon, and vpon as good ground, wee may hold an vniuerſall reprobation vpon the condition of incredulitie, as an vniuerſall election vpon condition of faith.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, it ſerueth to refute ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther error of the ſame perſons, who holde that the difference betweene man &amp; man is not made in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2933:31"/>of God, but wholly conſiſteth in the will of man; for by their doctrine, Gods mercie is extended vnto all, not onely in the decree, but euen in the execution of it, ſo that as God from all eternitie hath appointed to ſaue all, if they doe beleeue, ſo in time hee giueth them grace and power to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, if they will; for ſo they define their vniuerſall grace, <hi>an habitude or power to beleeue, if they will.</hi> But of theſe men I demaund then whence comes the acting and confirming of this generall power, that ſome doe indeed beleeue, and ſome doe not, ſome perſeuere in faith, ſome do not? If it ſhall be anſwered, that it procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from another ſpeciall grace of God, (which were the ſafeſt) then I aske, why doth God giue this ſpeciall grace to act and confirme faith in ſome, and not in others? no reaſon can be rendred but his will: ſo then by this reaſon the will of God ſhall put the difference betweene man and man, and not mans will. If it ſhall be ſaid, that it comes of the will of man, it ſmelleth ſtrongly of Pelagianiſme: for howſoeuer they would cloake all vnder the name of grace, and ſeeme to attribute nothing vnto nature, but
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2933:32"/>all vnto grace; yet they cannot ſcape ſo, for all men deſcending of <hi>Adam</hi> hauing equall grace, how commeth it to paſſe, that his generall power is acted in ſome, and not in otherſome? Anſwere is made, becauſe ſome will beleeue, ſome will not, ſome will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuere, ſome will not: what is this elſe but to attribute the whole ſaluation of man to his owne will, and to the power of nature, conſidering that ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation followeth not neceſſarily of grace, which is common to all, but of the acting and confirmation of it, which is wholly aſcribed to the will of man without any ſpeciall grace?</p>
                  <p>The vſe of inſtruction is this, that ſeeing God hath thus ſorted and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed men in his decree, and no cauſe thereof is knowne vnto vs, wee ought with feare and aſtoniſhment to ſubmit our ſelues vnto the good will and pleaſure of God, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence that myſterie which our rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon cannot comprehend, following the modeſtie of <hi>Dauid,</hi> Pſal. 36. where co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering of the vnſearchable iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God crieth out, that his iudgements are a great deepe, which cannot bee ſounded by the ſlender and ſhallow reaſon of man; and of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2933:32"/>
                     <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 11.33. where hauing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed at large of the reiection of the Iew, and the election of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, breaketh out into the admiration of the vnſearchable and vnconceiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able iudgements of God. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> alſo had well taken out this leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, who conſidering of this great and high myſterie, and the ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of it, why God draweth ſome, and not otherſome? why hee giueth perſeuerance to ſome, and not to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? why hee chuſeth ſome, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth others? hee doth not reaſon the matter, but admireth and ſaith, <hi>O Altitudo!</hi> And this ſobrietie of iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment haue all Gods children practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in all ages, neither may we carpe and cauill at that which for the depth and profoundnes of it wee are neuer able to conceiue. Thus much ſhall ſuffice to haue ſpoken of the generall doctrine, and of the vſe thereof: now let vs deſcend to a more particular handling and examining of the text.</p>
                  <p>And to ſpeake of the words as they lie in the text; whereas the Apoſtle ſaith, God <hi>hath not appointed vs, &amp;c.</hi> it is manifeſt that there is a number of men in the decree of God appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to wrath, or there is a decree of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2933:33"/>Reprobation; the which that wee may the better vnderſtand may bee thus deſcribed. Reprobation is the decree of God, by which vpon his owne will he hath purpoſed to refuſe certaine men for the manifeſtation of his iuſtice. For the cleering of this deſcription theſe foure points offer themſelues to bee conſidered. Firſt, the obiect or matter of this decree. Secondly, the order of it. Thirdly, the impulſiue cauſe. Fourthly, the end.</p>
                  <p>Touching the firſt. The thing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed is the reiection of certaine men; neither may this ſeeme ſtrange or hard to any, for God is a moſt abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and ſoueraigne Lord, and may doe with his owne what he will, and therefore may open the gates of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and admit into his kingdome whom hee will, and therefore may barre the gates and ſhut out whom he will, and who can controle him, or iuſtly reprehend him? Is any mans eye euill becauſe he is good? or doth God vſe partialitie, or acceptation of any mans perſon? Nothing leſſe: for vnto the one (as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>epiſt.</hi> 105.</note>) he giueth <hi>indebitam gratiam,</hi> and to the other <hi>debitam poenam.</hi> The Scripture alſo is pregnant in this point. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbs
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2933:33"/>16.4. God hath made all things for himſelfe, yea the wicked man to the day of euill. Rom. 9.22. There are veſſels of wrath fitted or framed to deſtruction: in this place ſome are appointed vnto wrath. <hi>Iude</hi> verſe 4. there is mention of certaine falſe tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, that were of old ordained vnto condemnation, neither are they or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to the end alone, but to the meanes alſo. 1. Pet. 2.8. Chriſt is a ſtone to ſtumble at, and a rock of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to certaine men, which ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at the word, being diſobedient, vnto the which thing they were euer ordained. Why ſhould we then be ſquemiſh or afraid to ſpeake with the Scripture, that God hath reiected ſome men, and purpoſed to glorifie his name in their deſerued condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
                  <p>The order of this decree follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: wherein we are to conſider, firſt of all that God for his part, as he doth conceiue all things at once, and not ſucceſſiuely one thing after another, but paſt, preſent, &amp; to come, at once, with one eternall and immutable act of vnderſtanding; ſo hee doth decree all things at once, and not ſucceſſiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: the reaſon is plaine, becauſe all
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:2933:34"/>things are preſent vnto him; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are not greatly to contend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the order, there being no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of it in God, in whom there is neither <hi>prius</hi> nor <hi>posterius.</hi> Yet for the helping of our weakenes in this high myſterie, we may diſtinguiſh the counſell of God in this point, into two acts or degrees, the which that we doe not in any wiſe miſconceiue, this ground muſt be laid: That what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer God hath decreed, hee hath done it moſt wiſely: now wiſedome requireth that a man ſhould thinke firſt of the end, &amp; then of the meanes, and therefore determine firſt touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the end, and then after touching the meanes: now the end which God propoundeth vnto himſelfe in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of Reprobation, is partly the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of his wrath expreſſed in this text, and partly of his power and iuſtice, Rom. 9.22. The firſt act there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of this decree may not (as I take it) be vnfitly thus conceiued. It is the decree of God wherein hee hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to paſſe by ſome men, that in them hee might manifeſt his wrath and iuſtice. This act is called by ſchoolemen the priuatiue or nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue reprobation, becauſe God in it
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:2933:34"/>denieth to giue grace, and by ſome later Diuines the decree of preteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And it hath not any cauſe out of God in the creature.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond act is the ordaining of the creature vnto iuſt puniſhment, which is termed in Schooles the poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue or affirmatiue reprobation. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, this act in regard of the obiect hath a double conſideration, the one is ſimple, as it reſpecteth this or that particular man, as <hi>Pharaoh, Saul, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das,</hi> comparatiue, as it reſpecteth this man and not that, as <hi>Pharach,</hi> and not <hi>Moſes; Saul,</hi> and not <hi>Dauid; Iudas,</hi> and not <hi>Peter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The impulſiue cauſe of the priua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, or negatiue reprobation, is no other then the will of God, as it may appeare, Romans 9.22. What if God would, &amp;c. and in the ſame chapter, verſe 18. no other reaſon is rendred, (why God hardneth the hearts of men, that is, hauing offered the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> means of mollifying their hearts, and hauing put into their mindes good motions, doth ſuffer them notwithſtanding to abuſe them to their greater harde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and hereupon in his iuſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doth deliuer them vp to Satan and their owne concupiſcences as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:2933:35"/>torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tors, that they become more obdurate and obſtinate in ſinne, and ſo worke their owne woe, and in fine make vp the meaſure of their owne damnation) ſaue onely the will of God, whom hee will hee hardeneth: neither is there any other reaſon ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of the hatred of <hi>Eſau,</hi> then of the loue of <hi>Iacob.</hi> Likewiſe our Sauiour Chriſt, Matth. 11.25.26. yeeldeth no reaſon of the reuelation of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell to ſome, and the hyding from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſaue the good pleaſure of God; <hi>Euen ſo O Father becauſe it pleaſed thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But this ſeemeth hard vnto many to aſcribe vnto God (whom the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures euery where deſcribe to bee full of bountie, and mercie, and ſlow to wrath) ſuch a decree and that vpon his owne will: let vs therefore conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their reaſons.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, they hold it to be a matter of crueltie and rigour for God thus to purpoſe the reprobation of man. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere.</hi> Shall it bee no crueltie in man (who is but a pettie Lord, or rather a Tenant at will, hauing all his intereſt and title vnto the creatures by grant and conceſſion from God) to kill an oxe or a ſheepe for his vſe, to hunt or
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:2933:35"/>to kill the Hare or the Partridge for his pleaſure? and ſhall God (who is a moſt abſolute and ſoueraigne Lord ouer all creatures) be accuſed and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigned of crueltie and ſeuere dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, if vpon his will he do refuſe and forſake his creature for his glorie?</p>
                  <p>Further it is obiected; That he that ordaineth to the end which is dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, ordaines to the meanes which is ſinne; but hee ordaines to the end. <hi>Ergo.</hi> and ſo by this doctrine God ſhall bee made the author of ſinne. <hi>Anſw.</hi> The ſupreme end which God propoundeth vnto himſelfe in this decree is not the deſtruction of man, but the declaration of his iuſtice: the appointed meanes to this end is not ſinne on Gods part, which is euill in it ſelfe; but the iuſt and voluntarie permiſſion of ſinne, which is good: ſinne therefore in it ſelfe is no effect of the decree of God, but an Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent thereunto, yea euen a procuring and meritorious cauſe of actuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, that is, damnation.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly it is replied, that if God vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his wil hath decreed to condemne any, he ſhall be contrarie to himſelfe: for in his word he hath reuealed, that hee willeth not the death of a ſinner,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:2933:36"/>Ezech. 33.11. but that all men ſhould be ſaued, &amp;c. 1. Tim. 2.4. <hi>Anſw.</hi> A ſinner muſt be conſidered either as he is man, or as he is a ſinner, as
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ad Simplic. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>qu.</hi> 2.</note> 
                     <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> anſwereth, God is not deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the death of a ſinner as he is a man, but as hee is a ſinner, neither that ſimply as it is the ruine and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of the creature,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Aug. de Corrup. &amp; grat. cap.</hi> 14.</note> or the putting of him foorth vnto puniſhment, but as it is an illuſtration of the glorie of God and execution of his iuſtice. Touching the latter place it maketh nothing for the purpoſe, being right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly interpreted. For where it is ſaid, God would haue all men ſaued, the word (
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Particula om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis non ſemper collectiuè, ſed ſaepe diſtributiue vt hic ſumitur. Vid. Ariſt. Polit. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> All) muſt not bee taken vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſally, but indefinitly, according to the ancient expoſition of <hi>Augustine,</hi> not all and euery one, but of all ſome; not <hi>ſingula generum,</hi> but <hi>genera ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>orum.</hi> And this meaning agreeth very fitly vnto the text: for the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle hauing in the firſt verſe exhorted that prayers and ſupplications ſhould be made for all men, leſt he ſhould be miſtaken, (as though his meaning were, that all men, euen reprobates detected, and ſinners againſt the holy Choſt, ſhould be prayed for,) he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds himſelfe in the next verſe: for
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:2933:36"/>Kings, and for all that are in authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that is, for all ſtates, degrees, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and conditions of men. Now in the fourth verſe he vrgeth his exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation by a reaſon, wherein the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall note muſt bee equally exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as before; the reaſon ſtandeth thus: Thoſe whom God would haue ſaued ought to be prayed for; but of all ſorts and conditions of men God would haue ſome to be ſaued. <hi>Ergo.</hi> The propoſition is concealed, the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption is laid downe in the fourth verſe, the concluſion is the exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the firſt verſe: and that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee taken generally, the context doth plainly declare in that all come not to the knowledge of the truth, that is, of the Goſpell, neither poſſibly can doe, ſeeing to many it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God in all ages to denie all means of reuelation. Againe, all men that are ſaued, God would haue them ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; as if a man ſhould ſpeake of the gates of a citie, all men enter in by theſe gates, that is, all that doe enter: for it were abſurd to ſay that all men liuing enter into that citie:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 107. <hi>ad ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talem. &amp; Ench.</hi> 103. <hi>&amp; cap.</hi> 8. <hi>de oredeſt, ſanct.</hi>
                     </note> ſo <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> alſo expoundeth.</p>
                  <p>Againe, both the word of God, and <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his book
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 15. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> 
                     <hi>de ciuit. Dei,</hi>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:2933:37"/>diſtinguiſheth mankinde into two companies or ſocieties, of both which vniuerſall propoſitions are giuen out: as for example, of the elect, that they ſhall be all taught of God: of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate, that euery man ſeeketh his owne; ſo it is ſaid here God would haue all men to bee ſaued, that is, the elect: for ſo the propoſition is to bee reſtrained vnto the matter ſubiect, there being alſo an vniuerſalitie of the elect.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, the place may bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood fitly not of all men deſcending from <hi>Adam,</hi> but of al men in the laſt age of the world, that is, of Iewes, and Gentiles; for in the three formes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, there was alwaies a difference betweene man and man, people and people: in the firſt age ſome were the ſonnes of God, ſome the ſonnes of men: in the ſecond age ſome the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the promiſe, ſome of the fleſh: in the third age ſome were Iewes, ſome Gentiles: but in the fourth age, at the aſcenſion of Chriſt, this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence hath been taken away, and the promiſe of grace and mercie, at leaſt in regard of the propounding of it, made common to all people. And that this is the meaning of the place,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:2933:37"/>
                     <hi>Paul,</hi> who is the beſt interpreter of himſelfe, plainly ſheweth; Act. 17.30. the times of ignorance, &amp;c. but now he admoniſheth all men euery where to repent. Rom. 16.25.26. The my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie was kept hid from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world, but now is opened and publiſhed among all nations. So Coloſſ 1.26.27.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, the will of God in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures is vſed two waies: firſt, it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth the decree, and is called by Schoolemen <hi>voluntas beneplaciti.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the reuealed wil, and ſo is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>voluntas ſigni:</hi> by the latter hee willeth that all men ſhould be ſaued, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> the offereth grace &amp; the means of ſaluation to all, not by the former according to the diſtinction vſed by ſome Diuines; he willeth the ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all, <hi>quoad preceptionem &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probationem, ſed non quoad gratiam &amp; efficaciam.</hi> But here it will be replied, that then there ſhall be two willes in God one contrarie to another. <hi>Anſw.</hi> To will and to nill the ſame thing doth not bring in a contrarietie, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe one and the ſame reſpect be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued in both. Now God in ſome reſpects willeth the ſaluation of men, that is, offereth the meanes principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:2933:38"/>that they might bee the more inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable, and in other reſpects, and for other iuſt &amp; neceſſary cauſes knowne to himſelf nilleth their ſaluation, that is, willeth not to make the meanes ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall vnto them. What is more vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all with men then to will and nill the ſame thing? but yet without contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie. For example: A man willeth the death of his father ſo farre foorth as it may put an end to his miſerie, and be a meanes to bring him to reſt and happineſſe; and hee nilleth it in another reſpect ſo farre foorth as he is thereby depriued of neceſſarie help and comfort.</p>
                  <p>The vſe of this doctrine followeth:
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                     </label> Firſt it ſerueth to ouerthrow the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of thoſe men that aſcribe the cauſe of reprobation vnto the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeene infidelitie of men and contempt of grace: for hereof it ſhould follow, that not the will of God, (as we haue ſufficiently proued before) but fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeene infidelitie ſhall bee the impul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue cauſe of reprobation, which is a manifeſt vntruth. For how many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate infants die in the Church? and how many are borne deaffe, which neuer heard the ſound of the Goſpell, much leſſe vnderſtood it,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:2933:38"/>how much leſſe contemned it: many alſo liuing out of the boſome of the Church haue not ſo much as heard of the Goſpell. Beſides, <hi>Paul,</hi> Gal. 5.20. numbreth vp many other cauſes of damnation beſides infidelitie, <hi>viz.</hi> all the workes of the fleſh, which make men as ſubiect to the wrath of God, and euerlaſting condemnation, as the other: and in the Lords prayer wee are taught to aske, not the pardon of one ſinne onely as of infidelitie, but plurallie of many treſpaſſes. Yea, though there were no contempt of the Goſpell, nor any poſitiue infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the originall corruption of mans nature were ſufficient to condemne all men. Laſtly, the admitation wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into <hi>Paul</hi> breaketh, Rom. 9.20. O man what art thou, that takeſt part to diſpute againſt God! doth plainlie ſhew that the decree of God in reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting ſome men hath an vnſearchable cauſe, and doth not depend of any foreſeene contempt of grace, for ſo there might eaſily be rendred a reaſon of the decree of God.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, if God hath appointed to reiect and paſſe ouer ſome men, it is the dutie of euery one to labour to be aſſured that he is exempted out of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:2933:39"/>the number of that companie. 2. Tim. 2.21. Whoſoeuer purgeth himſelfe from theſe, that is, errors in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and vncleannes in life, may aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure himſelfe that he is a veſſel of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour ſanctified vnto the Lord, and prepared to euery good worke. And contrariwiſe to bee in the number of the elect, obeying the counſell of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> 2. Epheſ. chap. 1. verſ. 10. in vſing al diligence to make ſure his election by the practiſe of a holie life. The Diſciples of our Sauiour Chriſt ſo ſoone as they heard this voyce vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<note place="margin">Matth. 26.</note> 
                     <hi>One of you ſhall betray me,</hi> preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly began to equire among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, and to demaund of Chriſt whether it it were they or no? carrying a holie ſuſpition of their traiterous hearts: ſo likewiſe hearing this voyce dailie ſounding in the Church, that there is a number of men in the counſell of God reiected, which ſhal periſh euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly; wee are to examine our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, and to make queſtion whether it be we or not? rather then curiouſly to ſearch the reaſon of that which we cannot conceiue. And if we ſhal finde his mercie to bee extended toward vs in preparing vs vnto glorie, let vs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it with thankfull hearts,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:2933:39"/>make ſpeciall account of it, and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the riches of his grace vnto vs.</p>
                  <p>The laſt point followeth, that is, the end of this decree, which is the manifeſtation of the glorie of his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and iuſtice, Rom. 9.22. This alſo confuteth another error of the Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans, that imagining God made all of mercie, hold and teach that the end of all his counſels and decrees is to communicate his goodneſſe and mercie in eternall happineſſe to all his creatures. But they are greatly decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, for the nature of God is to be as iuſt, as mercifull, and therefore his decree muſt be anſwerable, for it may not in any wiſe contrarie his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
                  <p>Againe, God is as good in his iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, &amp; the execution thereof, as in his mercie. Though therefore the Lord, being goodneſſe it ſelfe, intend the communication of it vnto all his creatures, yet not in like ſort, but after a diuers manner, vnto ſome in mercy, vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in iuſtice.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:2933:40"/>
                  <head>A SERMON, WHICH SHEWETH HOW THE CHILDE OF God is neither ſubiect to the dominion of ſinne, nor total <hi>defection from grace.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>1. IOHN 3.9.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Whoſoeuer is borne of God, ſinneth not: for his ſeede rentaineth in him, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can he ſinne, becauſe he is borne of God.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the purpoſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the Apoſtle in this whole Epiſtle, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the faithful to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he writ in the doctrine of the Goſpell and the practiſe thereof, ſpecially in the maine and principall point of Chriſtian and brotherly loue, to the end they might bee well furniſhed with ſpiritual ioy, and aſſured of their fellowſhip &amp; communion with God: whereupon hee propoundeth vnto them theſe two points of faith and loue, handling the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> confuſedly, and by courſe paſſing from the one to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:2933:40"/>Further, he amplifieth both theſe by their contraries, diſſwading them both from ſeducers and Idols, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo from the loue of the world, &amp; the hatred of their brethren: hauing therefore made entrance in the two former chapters into this doctrine, now hee proceedes in the ſame argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, exhorting the faithfull in this third chapter to the ſtudie of holines in generall, and more ſpecially to the loue of their brethren. And in the firſt verſe hee ſetteth downe the dignitie and excellencie of the children of God, noting it to be a matter of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular preferment, &amp; preeminence for a man to be called the ſonne of God: which ſentence he further amplifieth by a <hi>Prolepſis,</hi> wherein hee meeteth with the peruerſe iudgement both of the world, and alſo of the faithful ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants and children of God. As for the iudgement of the world he inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth that it is to bee contemned, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ariſeth of the ignorance of God, in the end of the firſt verſe. As for the faithfull (leſt they ſhould bee too much daunted and diſcouraged, through the manifold afflictions and croſſes whereunto they are ſubiect in this life) he oppoſeth vnto their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:2933:41"/>miſerable eſtate the future glorie and felicitie, which certainly abideth them after this life, which felicitie he defineth to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſt in a ſimilitude with God, and in a perfect ſeeing of him face to face, that is, in immediate fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip and coniunction with God: verſe 2. Now from the hope of this glorie and happineſſe hee exhorteth vnto the ſtudie of holineſſe, vrging the ſame by the example of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, verſ. 3. which exhortation he il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrateth by the contrarie, dehorting from ſinne, which is flat oppoſite vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to holineſſe, and that by diuers argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Firſt, from the nature of it, which is an anomie or tranſgreſſion of the law, verſ. 4. Secondly, from the end of Chriſt his firſt comming into the world, which was to take away ſinne, and to diſſolue the workes of the diuell, verſ. 5. and the latter end of the 8. Thirdly, from their communion and fellowſhip with Chriſt, in whom there was no ſinne, verſ. 6. Fourthly, from the author of ſinne, who is the diuell, whoſe ſocietie is by all meanes to bee auoided, verſ. 8. Fifthly, from the efficient cauſe of holineſſe, that is, regeneration, verſ. 9. wherein are laid downe theſe two points.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:2933:41"/>
Firſt, the deſcription of the ſtate and condition of a man regenerate by two arguments: the firſt whereof is taken from his nature, which is to be borne of God, which is as naturall vnto him, as it is naturall vnto a man to bee borne of his naturall parents: the ſecond is taken from the denied effect he ſinneth not.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, a reaſon, <hi>for his ſeed, &amp;c.</hi> In the latter end of the verſe there is an inuerſe repetition of the former branch, with an amplification from the cauſe. And this is the coherence and diſpoſition of theſe words: now let vs come to a more particular exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of them; and firſt ſearch the ſenſe &amp; proper meaning of them, and after deſcend to the doctrines and vſes which they ſhall affoord.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He that is borne of God</hi> that is,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Senſe. </seg>
                     </label> He that is renewed and ſanctified by the grace and ſpirit of God, being in his minde enlightened with the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the truth, and in his heart, will, affections, and the whole man framed and formed vnto the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence thereof: the which that it may be more cleere and manifeſt, it ſhall not bee amiſſe briefly to conſider the cauſes of our regeneration and new
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:2933:42"/>birth. The principall efficient is the holy Ghoſt, inſinuating himſelfe into the hearts of the elect, and effectually applying the forme and vertue of the death &amp; reſurrection of Chriſt, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by aboliſhing the corruption of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and creating an inherent quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of righteouſneſſe and holineſſe in the whole man, Rom. 8.9.10. The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentall cauſe is the word of God, that is, the immortall ſeede of rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, as the Apoſtle termeth it, 1. Pet. 1.21. The materiall cauſe is the efficacie or effect of that righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe which is inherent in the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature of Chriſt, from which as from a roote and fountaine is propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated and deriued all that holineſſe which is to bee found in the faithfull. 1. Cor. 1.30. Chriſt is made vnto vs from God righteouſneſſe, holineſſe, not onely by imputation vnto iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, but by infuſion vnto ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. The formall cauſe is the reno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the decaled image of God in the whole man, Ephe. 4.23.24. The finall cauſe is the worſhip of God in the duties of the firſt and ſecond ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Epheſ. 2.10. by all which we may ſee in part what regeneration is.</p>
                  <p>Now come we to the ſecond ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:2933:42"/>of the deſcription, which is the effect denied, hee <hi>ſinneth not:</hi> the meaning is not that the regenerate man is this life is whole pure and free from ſinne, for that is cleane contrary to the tenour of the whole Bible, and to common and manifeſt experience in the Church of God, and were here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie for a man once to conceiue. Eccl. 7.22. Prou. 20.9. 1. Ioh. 1.8. and the moſt holy men of God that euer haue liued in the Church, haue not onely been ſubiect vnto ſinne, but when the occaſions of temptation haue been greater, haue fallen dangerouſly and grieuouſly, as wee haue examples in <hi>Noah, Lot, Aaron, Dauid, Peter.</hi> The proper meaning therefore and ſenſe of theſe words is this: he ſinneth not, that is, he doth not laboriouſly, pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and diligently employ and buſie himſelfe in the practiſe of ſinne, hee ſinneth not with ſtudie, with delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, with conſtant purpoſe, with full conſent of will, with delight, with endeuour, with continuance: to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, hee makes not a trade and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupation of ſinning: for ſo much is comprehended in the phraſe, <hi>he ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not,</hi> or hee doth not practiſe ſinne.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:2933:43"/>
For the further cleering of this point, to commit ſinne containeth in it theſe three things: firſt, to giue full and free conſent vnto ſinne. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to giue vp the members of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to the practiſe of ſinne. Thirdly, to keepe a courſe and continuance in ſinne. Thus the man regenerate ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not: firſt, he doth not fully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vnto ſinne, as it may appeare in <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 7.16. where hee ſaith, that if hee did the euill, hee would not, hee co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſented to the law that it was good: if then hee did at all conſent vnto the law, he did not wholly conſent vnto ſinne, but more plainly, verſ. 22. <hi>For I delight in the law of God, &amp;c.</hi> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, hee doth not giue vp his members to the practiſe of ſinne: he is ſo farre from that, that he bridles and ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the corruption of nature in the heart, before it breake foorth into ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Gal 5.24. They that are Chriſts, that is, by faith vnited vnto him, they haue receiued the ſpirit of Chriſt, whereby they crucifie them with the affections and luſts. 1. Iob. 5.18. Hee that is borne of God, keepeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that is, preſerueth himſelfe from ſinne, ſo much as poſſibly he can. And this y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle inſinuateth, Rom. 6.19.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:2933:43"/>As you haue giuen vp your members, &amp;c. ſignifying that as by the force and ſtrength of naturall corruption, they did before regeneration proſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute the members of their bodies vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vncleannes and ſinne; ſo now by the vertue of Gods grace after their conuerſion, they ſhould ſanctifie all their parts vnto the practiſe of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes. Thirdly, hee keepeth not a courſe in ſinne, but either preſently, or not long after his fall, riſeth againe and recouereth himſelfe by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, as we haue examples in <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Peter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>1</label> The doctrine that we are to learne hence is two-fold: firſt, that the child of God in this life is exempted and priuiledged not from ſinne, but from the reigne, rule, and dominion of ſin wholly, from the power and bondage of it in ſome part: ſinne doth not at all rule in the childe of God, though the remainders of the corruption of nature haue power otherwhiles to bring foorth the fruites of the fleſh. This appeares plainly, Rom. 8.2. <hi>The lawe of the ſpirit of life which is in Chriſt Ieſus, hath freed me,</hi> not from ſinne, but <hi>è iure peccati;</hi> which thing alſo may bee further confirmed by
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:2933:44"/>theſe two reaſons. Firſt, where Chriſt hath taken the hold, there Satan is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled and caſt foorth: now Chriſt hath taken the poſſeſſion of euerie mans heart that is regenerate and borne againe, and therefore no place for Satan; for it is not poſſible that Chriſt by faith and grace, and Satan by corruption and ſinne, ſhould at once lodge and dwel together in one and the ſame heart: if Chriſt keepe the hold, Satan is excluded, if the ſtrong man be in poſſeſſion, all things are in peace, there is no roome for Chriſt. Secondlie, the perpetuall combate betweene the fleſh and the ſpirit, whereof the Apoſtle ſpeakes, Galath. 5.17. ſo that wee cannot doe what wee would, neither that good by reaſon of ſinne, nor that euill by reaſon of grace; which could in no wiſe be, if ſo be that ſinne raigned, for in the raigne of ſinne there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>1</label> But againſt this many things are excepted. Rom. 6.12. <hi>Let not ſinne raigne: Ergo,</hi> the Romanes who were iuſtified and ſanctified, and all rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate men, are ſubiect to the raigne of ſinne.</p>
                  <p>To this I anſwere,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> that the exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:2933:44"/>doth not imply any ſuch thing, only it ſheweth the perill and danger they might fall into by reaſon of ſin, that hereby they might loſe many of the graces of God, and depriue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues of all ſpirituall conſolation, and if it were poſſible wholly fall from grace, ſo as ſinne might againe beare rule in them. So alſo other exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in Scripture, as this, <hi>Hee that ſtandeth, let him take heed leſt he fall,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.12</note> doe not inſinuate that a man in the ſtate of grace may fall wholly, but in part, or they bewray his weakeneſſe conſidered in himſelfe whereby hee may wholly fall, or they are ſpurres to our dull ſides, and rods to our ſlow backs, to ſtirre vs vp to vigilancie and care, leſt we fall; nay rather they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie wee ſhall not fall, for they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments to preſerue from falling, God making good that which hee commaundeth in the hearts of the faithfull.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>2</label> But ſinne raigned in <hi>Dauid</hi> during the time of his impenitencie.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, it is not probable,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Solution. </seg>1</label> neither can it euer bee proued that the ſpirit of murther and adulterie did peaceably raign in <hi>Dauid</hi> for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpace of a whole yeere, without checke or controle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:2933:45"/>ſpecially hee being a man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Gods owne heart, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with moſt ſingular and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent graces of God.</p>
                  <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Solution. </seg>2</label> if we take raigning ſinne properly for that which is not reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted by the grace of the holy Ghoſt, we cannot in any wiſe aſcribe it vnto <hi>Dauid,</hi> for without doubt he reſiſted at the firſt aſſault, though peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the reſiſtance was more obſcure and inſenſible, by reaſon of the vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie and impetuouſnes of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, by the tumult and diſorder whereof the ſpirit of God ſpeaking in the conſcience was not heard or attended vnto, yet a reſiſtance there was, becauſe there was grace, which in the firſt temptation could not bee idle: But if wee take raigning ſinne for a preuailing ſinne, it cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied but that corruption for the time preuailed againſt grace.</p>
                  <p>Yea,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>3</label> but <hi>Paul</hi> confeſſeth of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe that he was carnall and ſold vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſinne, and therefore it may ſeeme that ſinne had dominion in him.</p>
                  <p>The anſwere is eaſie.
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Solution. </seg>
                     </label> The Apoſtle in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpeech alludeth vnto the bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaue; for there be two kindes of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, firſt, the vaſſal, which is bought
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:2933:45"/>and ſold with money, and ſecondly the hired ſeruant, which being at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, for ſome gaine bringeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe into voluntarie bondage: now <hi>Paul</hi> compares himſelfe vnto the ſlaue, who though he were very deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to eſcape his maſters hands, yet was conſtrained in great miſerie to ſerue him: ſo hee by reaſon of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques of originall ſinne, was other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whiles forced to ſerue ſinne in ſome part: but he doth not ſay that he was like to the hired ſeruant, who in hope of ſome profit, pleaſure or prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, did ſell himſelfe to worke wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, as <hi>Ahab.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>2</label> hence wee obſerue a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction betweene the naturall and regenerate man; the one being called in Scriptures a worker of iniquitie, the other no ſinner, though both of them fall into one and the ſame ſinne: the reaſon hereof is this, becauſe the one ſinneth with full purpoſe &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of will, hauing no grace at all to reſiſt; the other doth not conſent but in part, as it is manifeſt in the example of <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 7.22.23. and by theſe ſignes, firſt before hee ſinne hee doth not intend it, or deſire it, but hee pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth &amp; willeth the contrary good.
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:2933:46"/>Secondly, in the action hee reſiſteth leſſe or more, though peraduenture the reſiſtance bee not ſo euident, by reaſon of the violence of the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Thirdly, after the action hee is ſorrie and repents ſeriouſly.</p>
                  <p>An example hereof we haue in <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> who before his fall was reſolute rather to haue died, then denied his Maſter; in the action there was ſome ſlender reſiſtance, as may bee percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the anſwere hee made to the damoſell in his firſt aſſault, ſaying, <hi>I know not the man,</hi> coldly and remiſly, and after being admoniſhed partlie by the voyce of the Cocke, and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and principallie by the looke of our Sauiour Chriſt, hee went out and wept bitterly. All was contrarie in <hi>Iudas,</hi> who came with a reſolute minde to betray his Maſter; for the diuell hauing a long time tempted him hereunto, at the laſt entreth into him, that is, cauſeth him to reſolue to commit the trecherie, and in the temptation hee reſiſted not, being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together deſtitute of grace, and after hee repented not in a godly manner vnto ſaluation, but in a deſperate griefe went and diſpatched himſelfe.</p>
                  <p>The vſe of this doctrine is this:
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                     </label> By
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:2933:46"/>it as by a rule wee are directed to trie and examine our owne eſtate; for if we be regenerate and borne againe of God, wee haue not our conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in ſinne, we doe as much as poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble we can to abſtaine from ſinne; for if wee take our pleaſure, and lead our liues in ſinne, a plaine argument it is that we are not borne of God, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine as yet the ſonnes of the old <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam.</hi> If wee that liue in the ſchooles of the Prophets ſhould examine our ſelues by this rule, I feare me that the grace of regeneration would be very rare, or not at all found among vs: for the ſinnes which we doe, not of infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie and weakenes only commit, but euen of cuſtome and obſtinacie, and which raigne amongſt vs, doe plainly proue and conuince vnto our ſelues, that wee are deſtitute of the grace of regeneration. And firſt of all the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie, which ruleth amongſt vs, whereby we are frozen in our dregs, void of ſenſe, remorſe, and conſcience of ſinne, and of all feare of the wrath of God, as alſo of all feeling of the want of Chriſt, and of that ſpirituall hunger after him, and his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, doth euidentlie demonſtrate this. Againe, the contempt of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:2933:47"/>and the worſhip of God, which appeares in our aſſemblies, argues no leſſe, as well in the Preacher as in the hearer: for many a man comming in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this place to preach the word, doth not (as it is plaine by his pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe) propound vnto himſelfe the glorie of God, the edificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Gods Church, that is, the winning, ſauing and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerting of mens ſoules, which is the principall drift and maine ſcope of all the Scriptures, and of all our preaching and hearing; but hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to preach his wit, memorie, learning, reading, skill in Arts and tongues, vaine &amp; fooliſh eloquence. As for the hearers, ſome come of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome to heare the word, for forme and faſhion, either to retaine their credit, or to preuent the danger of law: ſome with preiudicate mindes to carpe and to cauill, and to take ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception againſt the ſpeaker, either for the matter or manner of deliuerie: ſome to haue their cares tickled with an emptie and idle ſound: ſome for this ſiniſter purpoſe, ſome for that; but few come with due preparation, with reuerent and religious mindes to haue their conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces edified, their hearts diſcloſed, the ſecrets of their
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:2933:47"/>thoughts reuealed, that they might be humbled, and conuerted vnto God: in both which the worſhip of God is abuſed and prophaned.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, the groſſe and palpable hypocriſie which is to bee found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, whereby we can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent all of vs to make profeſſion of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Chriſtianitie, but when it comes to the practiſe, there we faile: nay if any man ſhall giue himſelfe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly and conſtantly to the practiſe of religion, he ſhall be ſcorned, moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and reuiled with moſt odious and ignominious, yea with moſt hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and hereticall names. Further, this one thing bewraieth our hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie to al men, that whereas we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe loue vnto God and to our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, wee put in practiſe neither of both: for if we loued God, we would deſire to haue communion and fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with him, and conſequently the meane; whereby this fellowſhip is begun and preſerued, which are, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation in the word, inuocation, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and other exerciſes of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; which becauſe they are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally neglected, plainlie argue our want of the loue of God: And in ſtead of louing our brethren, in ſocieties
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:2933:48"/>there is to bee found hatred, malice, rancour, pride, and lifting vp of our ſelues againſt our brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, contempt, diſdaine, and ſuch like; al which make manifeſt the hypocriſie of our hearts.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly (to omit the abuſe of the name of God by blaſphemous oaths, and the prophanation of the Lords Sabbaths) the pride and exceſſe aſwel in apparell as in diet, doth plainly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince this point, ſpecially in theſe times wherein the Lord hath called vs to moderation and frugalitie: all which, with many moe ſinnes that raigne among vs, doe argue the want and the abſence of the grace of rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration.</p>
                  <p>But to leaue this poynt and to come to the reaſon, becauſe in it is is contained ſpeciall matter of inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: <hi>for his ſeede remaineth, &amp;c.</hi> By ſeede in this place (to omit all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther expoſitions) wee are to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the word of God, the immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ſeede of regeneration as <hi>Peter</hi> calleth it, which as it is in it ſelfe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall and incorruptible, ſo it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall &amp; incorruptible in the hearts of the Receiuers.</p>
                  <p>The doctrine that naturally ariſeth hence is this, that the childe of God
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:2933:48"/>begotten againe by the word and ſpirit of God, and indued with ſauing and effectuall grace, ſo continueth and abideth for euer: which point be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is difficult and controuerſall, I will ſtand the longer vpon it.</p>
                  <p>The queſtion then is this, whether ſauing grace may be wholy loſt, or not? For the better reſolution where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, we muſt hold and remember this diſtinction, that the word grace in Scripture, as alſo in the writings of Diuines is vſed two waies. Firſt, it is put for the loue, fauour and mercy of God, which is the fountaine and ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall of all grace, called by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, 2. Timoth. 1.9. the grace which was giuen vs through Chriſt Ieſus before the world was, and this is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall and immutable, as the Lord himſelfe, from which it is not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that a man ſhould euer totallie or finallie fall; according to that of our Sauiour Chriſt, Iohn 13.1. and that of the Prophet Eſay 54.9.10. Neuertheleſſe a man may looſe the ſignes and tokens of this grace wholy for a time; as it is manifeſt, Eſay 54.7.8. Pſalm. 89.30.31.32.33. And herein the Lord dealeth with his children, as the naturall Father with
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:2933:49"/>his child, who when he offendeth and tranſgreſſeth his commandement, he is angrie with him, hee lookes vpon him with a ſterne and ſeuere counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, he threatnes him to diſinherit him, and turnes all the tokens of his loue and fauour, into the ſignes of anger and diſpleaſure, yet he retaines this purpoſe firme and conſtant to make him his heyre: euen ſo doth the Father of ſpirits deale with his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, when they are rebellious and diſobedient vnto him, hee ſcourgeth them, he afflicteth them and lets them feele his diſpleaſure, yea, he puts them often in ſeare of depriuing them of the heauenly inheritance, yet his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of putting them in full poſſeſſion and giuing them the fruition hereof, neuer altereth, Pſalm. 89.33.34. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, it is put for the effects of this grace, which are of two ſorts; ſome are of abſolute neceſſitie vnto ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, without the which ſaluation and life eternall cannot be atchieued, as Election, effectuall vocation, iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, regeneration, and the graces thereof, hope, loue, the feare of God; and theſe can neuer be wholy loſt, as afterward wee ſhall prooue: ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine are neceſſarie, but not of abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:2933:49"/>neceſſitie, which may be loſt, as the inward cleanneſſe of the heart, the alacritie of ſpirit ariſing of a good conſcience, great boldneſſe in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſing and confeſſing the name of Chriſt, inuincible courage in bearing and ſuſtaining moſt grieuous croſſes, free and chearefull calling vpon the name of God, and an excellent ſenſe and taſte of the goodnes and mercy of God all which or the moſt of them were loſt in <hi>Dauid</hi> after his grieuous fall, as ſome haue obſerued out of the 51. Pſalme. To ſpeake more plainely and diſtinctly, ſpirituall ioy, the ſenſe and comfort of grace ariſing of the apprehenſion of the loue and fauour of God; the degree and meaſure of grace may bee wholy loſt for a time. Apoc. 2.4. the Church of Epheſus is reproued becauſe ſhe had left her firſt loue, which yerſt ſhee had profeſſed and practiſed; but no one grace of abſolute neceſſitie vnto ſaluation can euer be wholy loſt. This may appeare both by expreſſe teſtimonies of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as alſo by the euidence of reaſon deduced thence. Among many ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures I will make choyce of thoſe that are moſt pregnant for the purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>Matthew 16.18. The gates of hell
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:2933:50"/>though they may aſſaile the Church, and ioyne their forces againſt it, yet ſhall they neuer preuaile, becauſe it is built vpon the ſure foundation and rocke of our Sauiour Chriſt himſelfe, confeſſed by <hi>Peter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Iohn 3.36. He that beleeueth in the ſonne of God, hath preſently e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life. If it bee ſaid hee hath it in hope onely, not in deed; the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere is that the hope of Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren makes not aſhamed, Rom. 5. it doth not diſappoint a man of the thing hoped for, for why it is not a blinde hope, a vaine hope, a popiſh coniecturall hope, but a certaine and an infallible expectation of immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie and of the glory of God; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Dauid</hi> Pſalm. 31.1. ſaith, that he had caſt his hope vpon God, and therefore ſhould not bee confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
                  <p>Iohn 10.28.29. No man ſhall take my ſheepe out of my hands. <hi>Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> So long indeede as they conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue the ſheepe of Chriſt, none can take them from him. <hi>Anſwere:</hi> They alwaies ſo continue, as may appeare by the words following, they are the gift of the father, vnto the ſonne, and all which come vnto Chriſt are not
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:2933:50"/>caſt forth. Ioh. 6.37. and in the words following, the Father is greater then all: if then Satan, ſin, the fleſh, ſhould but for a time ſnatch them out of his hands, they ſhould at leaſt for a time be ſtronger then he.</p>
                  <p>Rom. 8.35.36.37.38.39. 1. Iohn 2.19. By all which places it is more then manifeſt that thoſe that are once in the ſtate of grace cannot wholy fall away.</p>
                  <p>But to deſcend to a more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar proofe and confirmation of this poynt: Firſt, Election cannot be loſt, for that is firme and vnchangeable. Rom. 9.11. <hi>Paul</hi> takes it for graunted that the purpoſe of God according to Election, might remaine firme and ſure, 2. Tim. 2.19. the foundation, that is, the Election of God which is the foundation of the ſaluation of the Elect, abideth firme and ſure.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, the effectuall calling of God is neuer made fruſtrate, but abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth alwaies: for it is without repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, Rom. 11.19.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Excep.</hi> God for his part repenteth not of any gift giuen vnto man; but man, after hee hath receiued grace from God, doth vnthankfully and contemptuouſly reiect it.</p>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:2933:51"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:2933:51"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:2933:52"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is not poſſible that any man ſhould reſiſt the powerfull ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the ſpirit of God in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; As for that of <hi>Stephen,</hi> Act. 7.51. (where hee vpbraides the Iewes that they had alwaies reſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ed the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt) it is to be vnderſtood of the ſpirit ſpeaking in the outward mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of the word, not inwardly and effectuallie working in the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, iuſtification ſtanding in the remiſſion of ſinnes, and accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a man vnto life, for the only o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bedience of Chriſt imputed, cannot bee made voide or fruſtrate: for the Lord doth moſt perfectly pardon ſin: Eſay 44.22. Micha. 7.19. Iere. 31.34. Pſal 103.12.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly and laſtly, Regeneration cannot be loſt: for why? the Author of it, that is, the ſpirit of God, abideth euer, 1. Ioh. 2.27. who is called the anointing and the oyle of gladneſſe, Pſalme 45.7. and the graces of it, as hope: for elſe how could it bee the anchor and hold of the ſoule? Heb. 6.19 Loue abideth euer, 1. Cor. 13.8. a ſeede whereof remained in <hi>Peter</hi> in his deniall, and the feare of God ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vtterly quaileth, Iere. 32.40.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:2933:52"/>
This alſo is manifeſt in experience: for when the childe of God yeeldeth to any grieuous temptation, hee ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not as one deſperate and voyde of all hope to bee recouered, nor of hatred againſt God, not in a ſecure contempt of God as the Epicure; but ſtill retaines in his heart ſome remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of theſe graces, which being af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward reuiued and quickned, hee raiſeth vp himſelfe and returnes vnto God. Grace in time of ſome grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous temptation is driuen into ſome narrow corner of the heart, euen as they that are in a Sconce or Caſtle beſieged, flie into ſome ſtreight cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, or ſome inward and ſecret place, yet after they come foorth. As then this point is cleere by Scriptures, ſo likewiſe reaſon will auouch and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate the ſame.</p>
                  <p>The firſt reaſon is taken from the interceſſion of Chriſt, who prayed not onely for <hi>Peter,</hi> Luke 22.32. but for all the elect that ſhould either then preſently, or hereafter beleeue, Ioh. 17.20. who was alwaies heard of his Father, Ioh. 11.42. Vnleſſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we will ſay that Chriſt his prayer is vneffectuall, wee muſt needes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that the beleeuer cannot whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:2933:53"/>be ouercarried of ſinne. And vnto this prayers of the faithfull, who aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in faith to bee ſtrengthened in temptation, that they might not wholly bee foiled, haue a promiſe to be heard. Vnleſſe therefore wee will ſay that God doth falſifie his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, we muſt neceſſarily affirme that the faithfull neuer fall totally from grace.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond is taken from the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall vnion, which is ſo firme and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſoluble that nothing can breake the ſame, Hoſ. 2.19. nay euen death it ſelfe doth not diſſolue this bond: for when the body is rotten in the graue and turned into duſt and aſhes, then notwithſtanding it remaines a part of that perſon which is really and truly (though ſpiritually) united vnto Chriſt, which is a matter of no ſmall comfort to the children of God: and if it could bee broken it could neuer bee reſtored, becauſe faith is but once giuen, Iude 3. And if it could bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored, and a new inſition into Chriſt made, then Baptiſme, which is the ſigne and ſeale hereof, muſt bee itera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and repeated for the confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof.</p>
                  <p>The third reaſon is this: If grace
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:2933:53"/>may be wholly loſt, then no man can bee aſſured of his ſaluation, neither can haue peace with God, nor pray in faith without doubting: but the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full man is certaine of his ſaluation, otherwiſe hee hath not faith, becauſe certaintie is of the nature of faith;
<note place="margin">Certitude eſt de natura fidei.</note> and hath peace with God, Rom. 5.1; and prayeth in faith without wauering, Iam. 1.6. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The fourth reaſon is this: The ſonne abides in the houſe for euer, that is, in the Catholike Church, Ioh. 8.35. but all the faithfull are ſons by adoption, Ioh. 1.12. and not onely ſonnes, but heires, and fellow-heires with Chriſt, Rom. 8.17. and therfore are neuer wholly caſt out of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of God, though they fall dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly. Now that we ſee this point to be ſo cleere and euident, let vs anſwer vnto ſome of thoſe obiections that are vſually alleaged to the contrarie, that wee may bee more confirmed in the preſent truth.</p>
                  <p>That election may be loſt,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                     </label> it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued out of <hi>Moſes</hi> prayer, Exod. 32.32. where <hi>Moſes</hi> prayeth to be blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of the booke of life.</p>
                  <p>To omit all other anſwers: firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Solution. </seg>
                     </label> that prayer is not abſolute but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionall,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:2933:54"/>and therefore affirmeth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing certainly. Secondly, it is not ſimple but comparatiue, rather then the whole bodie of the people ſhould periſh, and the glorie of God bee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached he prayeth in an earneſt affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to his brethren, and in a feruent zeale to Gods glorie, that hee might (if it were poſſible) bee raced out of the booke of life. As for the place in Pſalme 69.28. where <hi>Dauid</hi> prayeth that his enemies might be daſhed out of the booke of life, hee meaneth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate hypocrites, who though in their iudgement, and in the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church, were falſely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to bee in the number of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, yet their names were neuer writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in heauen, and therefore <hi>Dauid</hi> prayeth that the Lord would detect and make manifeſt their hypocriſie. But it will be replied, that the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Epheſus,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.4. 1 Theſſ. 1.4. 1. Pet. 1.1.</note> Theſſalonica, and the lewes are called Elect by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, who afterward notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding made totall defection and apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacie from God. <hi>Anſw.</hi> There be two kindes of iudgements to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of men; the iudgement of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie, whereby an infallible deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination is giuen of any mans parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:2933:54"/>eſtate: and this belongs to God properly and principally, and to man ſo farre foorth only as the Lord ſhall reueale the eſtate of one man to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: there is alſo the iudgement of charitie, wherby thoſe that liue in the Church &amp; haue giuen vp their names vnto God in Baptiſme, and profeſſe the religion of Chriſt, are commonly reputed to bee in the number of the Elect: and according to this latter iudgement did the Apoſtles ſpeake of the Churches. Againe, whole Churches are called Elect by a <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nechdoche</hi> by reaſon of the better and more excellent part, which are in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Elect: as the heape of corne, wherein there is a greater quantitie of chaffe is ſo called, by reaſon of the more principall part. As for the conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall decree it is a meere forgerie of mans braine, hauing no footing in the word of God: for to decree a thing conditionally is to decree no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all,
<note place="margin">Conditionalis propoſitio nihil ponit in eſſe.</note> becauſe the conditionall propoſition affirmes nothing; and beſides that it doth moſt indignely ſuſpend the will of God the ſupreme and ſoueraigne cauſe of all things, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering and ruling all ſecondary oau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and ouer-ruled by none vpon the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:2933:55"/>will of the creature: it doth moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piouſly aſcribe vnto God either im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudence or impotencie: for there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doe men purpoſe and decree things conditionally, either becauſe they know not what will bee the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent, or elſe are not able to effect that which they would: but God that hath al knowledge locked vp in his breaſt, and all power in his hand, hath no neede that hee ſhould conceiue any things of his decree with condition.</p>
                  <p>Againſt effectuall vocation it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged out of the Rom. 11.22.
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>2</label> whence (it ſeemes) may bee gathered, that a man effectually called and knit vnto Chriſt, may be againe cut off.</p>
                  <p>It is a Fallacian we call in ſchooles,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Solution. </seg>
                     </label>
                     <hi>Ignorantia Elenchi,</hi> for the Apoſtle ſpeakes not there of particular men, but of the whole body of the Iewes and the Gentiles, and hee oppoſeth the Gentiles vnto the Iewes, giuing the Iewes hope that if they ſhall not remaine in incredulitie and diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, but bee conuerted vnto God, both they and their poſteritie ſhould againe bee receiued into the boſome of the Church, and into the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the people of God: &amp; threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the Gentiles on the other ſide,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:2933:55"/>(among whom there were many, that had the faith of Chriſt more in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward profeſſion and appearance, then in the truth and power of godlineſſe) that if ſo bee at any time they ſhould depart from the doctrine of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, they ſhould be reiected, and the Iewes receiued in their roome and ſtead.</p>
                  <p>Againſt iuſtification, that is,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>3</label> remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſinnes, it is alleaged out of Matth. 18.32, 33, 34, 35. that pardon of ſinnes once giuen, by ſome conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent ſinne may be made voide.</p>
                  <p>Out of a parable no collection of doctrine may bee made befides the ſcope:
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Solution. </seg>
                     </label> the minde therefore of the ſpeaker, and the ſcope of the parable, and not the words, is to be weighed. Now our Sauiour Chriſt hauing taught immediatly before that iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries are to be pardoned, he by and by annexeth this parable for the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of his doctrine, thereby ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying that it is neceſſarie that thoſe that looke to haue their ſinnes pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of God, ſhould alſo pardon their brethren their treſpaſſes; and that they are deceiued who think to finde mercie with God in the pardon of their ſinnes, and yet carrie implacable
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:2933:56"/>and irreconcilable hatred towards thoſe that haue iniured them. So our Sauiour Chriſt expoundeth it in the laſt verſe: wherefore the onely thing that we can gather hence is this, That if wee ſhall not remit our brethren their treſpaſſes, wee ſhall incurre the anger and diſpleaſure of God; and that it is a plaine argument, that wee are not releaſed of our ſinnes before God, conſidering that our pardoning of our brethren their offences and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries they haue done to vs, is an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of our abſolution and diſcharge before God.
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Objection. </seg>4</label> 2. Pet. 1.9. The Apoſtle mentioneth ſome that had forgotten they were waſhed from their old ſins:
<note place="margin">Againſt Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration.</note> and 2. Pet. 2.20. ſome that had truly eſcaped them that were in error and filthineſſe of the world, were againe intangled therewith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Solution. </seg>
                     </label> The firſt place meaneth them that were waſhed in Baptiſme, called by the Apoſtle the lauer of regeneration, Tit. 3.5. who were purged onely <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramento tenus,</hi> or he ſpeaketh accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the iudgement of charitie. In the ſecond place he ſpeaketh of falſe teachers and hypocrites, as it is plaine by the context, and he doth not attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute vnto them the grace of Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:2933:56"/>but the knowledge of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Goſpell, and an outward reformation of manners; for theſe had truly eſcaped out of their old er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, and in ſtead thereof embraced the truth, and truly renounced their groſſe and notorious ſinnes, and did make a profeſſion of externall holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: yet afterward were intangled with their former hereſies and filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the world.</p>
                  <p>Further,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Solution. </seg>5</label> againſt this doctrine di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers examples are alleaged of them that haue made totall defection from grace,
<note place="margin">Examples.</note> as <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Dauid.</hi>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Solution. </seg>
                     </label> But theſe examples proue nothing: for firſt it may be doubted, whether <hi>Adam</hi> ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with full conſent of will or not, becauſe he (as <hi>Euah</hi>) was ſeduced by the ſubtiltie and iugling craftines of that old ſerpent, 2. Cor. 11.3. But be that granted, there is a great differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betweene <hi>Adam</hi> in the ſtate of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie, and the regenerate in the ſtate of grace: for though <hi>Adam</hi> had grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter grace, yea ſufficient grace to haue ſtood if he had would, yet he had not the grace of continuance; but the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate haue the grace of confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and perſeuerance, and herein the ſtate of regeneration is priuſledged
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:2933:57"/>before the ſtate of creation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>2</label> As for <hi>Dauid</hi> it is alleaged out of the 51. Pſalme, that hee prayed after his fall, that the Lord would create in him a new heart, now creation is of a thing that is not neither actually nor potentially, <hi>Ergo,</hi> hee was wholy for the time depriued of grace.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Solution. </seg>
                     </label>
                     <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeakes of himſelfe not as howas indeede before God, but as he was in his owne ſence, oppreſſed with the burden of his ſinnes, and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending in conſcience the anger and diſpleaſure of God for the ſame; whereupon as one forlorne and deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of all grace hee deſires the Lord to frame and create in his heart the graces of his ſpirit.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Except.</hi> Where there is no repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, there is no remiſſion of ſinnes, where there is no remiſſion, there is no faith, where there is no faith, there is no grace, and therefore <hi>Dauid</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time of his impenitencie had no grace.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Where there is no repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance neither habituall nor actuall, there is no grace. Againe, though there be no actuall remiſſion of ſins, but where there is both actuall faith and actuall repentance, yet the ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:2933:57"/>remiſſion is ſtill ratified, and the future pardon is purpoſed to bee beſtowed ſo ſoone as a man ſhall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually beleeue and repent, Laſtly, there may bee habituall grace, where there is no actuall remiſſion of ſome preſent particular ſinne or ſinnes for a time.</p>
                  <p>Not content with theſe,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                     </label> they vrge reaſon:
<note place="margin">From reaſon.</note> no man can bee a member of Chriſt and of an harlot at once, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Apoſtle oppoſeth them, 1. Cor. 6.16. and therefore hee that is ioyned and made one fleſh with an harlot is cut off from Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>A man is a member of Chriſt two waies: firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Solution. </seg>
                     </label> in reſpect of vnion and inſition which is perpetuall: ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in reſpect of communion and effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacie of the ſpirit; now then howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer he may be cut off in ſome part, that is, in regard of the inward fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip and communion with Chriſt, yet not wholy in reſpect of coniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with him: yea, though hee may become no liuely member, yet hee remaines a liuing member, though dead for a ſeaſon in regard of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and efficacie of the life of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. A mans arme taken with a dead Palſie, hangs by, and receiues no
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:2933:58"/>heate, life, or ſenſe from the reſt of the members, or from the head, yet for all this it remaines ſtill vnited and coupled to the body, and may againe bee recouered by plaiſters and Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke: ſo after a grieuous fall the child of God feeles no inward peace and comfort, but is ſmitten in conſcience with the trembling of a ſpirituall pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie for his offence: and yet indeed ſtill remaines before God a member of Chriſt in reſpect of his coniunction with him, and ſhall be reſtored to his former eſtate after ſerious repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>2</label> Grace cannot ſtand with ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the conſcience, and with grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous offences.</p>
                  <p>Though it cannot ſtand ſo firmely,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Solution. </seg>
                     </label> yet it is not wholy taken away, for a man in this caſe when ſinne hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed, is like vnto a building whoſe roofe is taken off with an earthquake or thunderbolt, and whoſe foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is ſhaken and weakened, yet the houſe ſtandeth ſtill. Secondly, wee muſt diſtinguiſh of ſinne againſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; for it is taken two waies, firſt properly, which is done of purpoſe, and with full conſent of will, and is called <hi>peccatum vastans conſcientiam,</hi>
                     <pb n="83" facs="tcp:2933:58"/>the ſinne that waſteth the conſcience, and this is not incident vnto the man regenerate: ſecondly, improperlie, which is done though of knowledge, yet of infirmitie by reaſon of feare, conſtraint, haſtineſſe, precipitation of the minde and ſuch like ſuddaine paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in the tegenerate, or with ſome wilfulneſſe of preſumption: yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is neuer any full and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute conſent, it cannot bee called ſinne againſt the conſcience properly. Wherefore to conclude this whole matter, we graunt that the man rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate and indued with ſauing grace, may fall into ſinne dangerouſlie and grieuouſlie, ſo as hereby his faith ſhall be weakened, his heart hardened, the ſpirit of God made ſadde in him, the peace of the conſcience troubled, the proceedings of Gods grace in the heart interrupted, the comfort and ioy of the ſpirit remooued, and the heart filled with amazedneſſe, aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, perplexitie and feare, all the grates of God leſſened, the beſt things in man obſcured and blemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, the courſe of Gods mercies ſtopped, and the whole man laid o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to all the plagues &amp; iudgements of God, and made vnprofitable to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:2933:59"/>good worke: yea, he may ſo fall that hee ſhall haue need of a new re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation with God, a new remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſion of his late offence, a new confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of faith, a new inkindling of the ſpirit, and a new reſtoring of the inner man: but that hee can wholy loſe grace, that is not poſſible; that, that faith which purifieth the heart and worketh by loue; that, that loue which proceedeth from a pure heart, a good conſcience and faith vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; that, that hope which maketh not aſhamed, and is the anchor hold of the ſoule firme and ſtedfaſt; that, that feare which is the headſpring of wiſdome, and cauſeth a man to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline from euill, and is in the heart a well of life to make a man ſcape the ſnares of death, can bee wholy loſt, neither ſcriptures, reaſon nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balitie ſhall be euer able to euince.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                     </label> The vſe of this doctrine is brieflie thus much, as on the one ſide it mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreth great comfort vnto the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God touching the perpetuitie of their eſtate, that though they ſhall bee aſſailed with dangerous and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold temptations, and be oftentimes fearefully foiled and ouertaken, yet that they ſhall neuer be wholy ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carried
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:2933:59"/>in any temptation: ſo on the other ſide it giueth vs a caueat to take heed we doe not abuſe it to ſecuritie and the libertie of the fleſh, for conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the ſtate of a chriſtian man is ſo tickle and inconſtant in this life, that he is ſubiect euer and anon to fall into ſinne, yea wholy to fall away, if it were not that by the promiſe of God, and the effectuall interceſſion of Chriſt, he were as by certaine vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>props ſupported and ſuſtained; requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite and neceſſarie it is that we liſten vnto the exhortation of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, and with feare and trembling to worke our ſaluation, and if any man thinke he ſtandeth, let him take heed leaſt he fall.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2933:60"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2933:60"/>
                  <p>TWO SERMONS, PREACHED BY THAT Reuerend and Iudicious Diuine Maſter THOMAS NEVVHOVSE, late Preacher of Gods word in the Citie of <hi>Norwich.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AND NOW SET FOORTH for the vſe and benefit of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, by ROBERT GALLARD Maſter of Arts, and Miniſter <hi>in the ſame Citie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>ECCLESIAST. 12.11.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>The words of the wiſe are as goads and nailes faſtned by the Maſters of the aſſemblies, which are giuen from one ſhepheard.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>AT LONDON Imprinted by <hi>Felix Kyngſton,</hi> for <hi>Edmund Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer</hi> and <hi>William Welby.</hi> 1614.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2933:61"/>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:2933:61"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL AND trulie religious Gentleman, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter THOMAS CORBET Eſquire,</hi> one of his Maieſties Iuſtices of Peace <hi>in the Countie of Norffolke: And to the Worſhipfull Gentlewoman Miſtris ANNE CORBET his moſt louing, wiſe, and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous wife: R G. wiſheth true hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe in this life, and a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed hope of the life to come.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Worſhipfull, thoſe exquiſite and moſt cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious workes, which <hi>Aholiab</hi> and <hi>Beza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leel</hi> wrought in the Temple, were to bee ſeene long after their times, and remained as teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of their skil to them that did ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiue: And we ſee alſo in common ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, that earthly buildings, when the workmen be dead, oft times ſtand ſtill as monuments of their art, and meanes of much good to them that
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:2933:62"/>liue after. In like manner it were to be wiſhed that the workes of the skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full builders vp of Gods houſe (when they themſelues bee gone) might ſtill continue as memorials of their skill in ſpirituall Architecture, and as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of much good to ſucceeding generations.</p>
                  <p>Among diuers workes of worthie workmen, who haue of late very arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficially and cunningly wrought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the temple of Chriſt, I am ſure that ſome of the Manuſcripts of that iudicious Diuine Maſter <hi>Thomas Newhouſe,</hi> may well for their art be valued with the beſt in their kinde, and cannot doubtleſſe but bee very precious in your eyes, who loued their author ſo well, and very profitable to many others, by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be ſo much deſired. For this cauſe (hauing ſome of them by me) leſt I ſhould ſeeme in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurious either to their author, in ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsing that which might make ſo much to his praiſe, or to the publique good, in keeping backe thoſe things are much deſired as vſefull to Gods
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:2933:62"/>people, I thought it a meete thing to publiſh theſe few to the making vp of this little volume.</p>
                  <p>Among the manifold true harted and entirely affecting friends this godly man had, I doubt not but that I might ſingle out diuers, of whoſe kindnes I might preſume for defence of his workes, and may iuſtly feare for paſsing them by, to be challenged as a man vnmindfull of their loue; but the time is comming wherein I hope to meete with good opportunitie of giuing them ſatisfaction in this kinde. In the meane while, I thinke it my dutie to remember your Worſhips with theſe; which if I had neglected to doe, I ſee not but that I ſhould in ſome meaſure haue been blemiſhed with the tincture of vnthankfulnes. I therefore doe offer theſe Sermons to your view, and alſo to your protectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, hoping that you ſhal finde them wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of both. If you reſpect their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, they bee his <hi>ſomething;</hi> if me the <hi>publiſher,</hi> alas they be my <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing:</hi> yet ſure ſuch is your ingenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:2933:63"/>as that I doubt not but that you will receiue them as pledges of loue, both his and mine.</p>
                  <p>Indeede I acknowledge the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular reſpects whereby it hath pleaſed your Worſhips to ingage me vnto you, doe farre exceed all that poore recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, which the ſlender dedication of theſe few ſheetes of paper can poſsiblie make; neither would I that the ſame ſhould bee taken as any way equali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing your deſert, but onely I deſire herein to giue you partly a ſigne of my dutifull and moſt vnfained affection towards you, and partly alſo a memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall of the Author, your departed friend, who is now in bleſſe; not doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting but that your Worſhips will pleaſe to giue a kinde acceptance to this my poore offer, not weighing the worth of the thing it ſelfe, but rather (as you are wont) the minde and good will of him that giueth.</p>
                  <p>Now for theſe two Sermons, in them the Author doth chiefly treate of theſe two things: <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> and the <hi>feare of God:</hi> the firſt, a ſigne
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:2933:63"/>of our inſition into Chriſt, and a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſeale of the couenant of grace. The ſecond is called in Scripture, the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerence of Iehouah,</hi> the fountaine or wel-ſpring of true and heauenlie wiſedome.</p>
                  <p>As touching Baptiſme me thinkes when wee ſeriouſly conſider with our ſelues what weighty things were done therein, and mutually paſt twixt God and vs, we cannot but ſee it to be vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly a fault, ſo eaſily to caſt aſide all thoughts about it, and to make it ſuch a ſtranger to our meditations as vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally wee doe. For mine owne part I know not whether any one thing be more worthie of a Chriſtians conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration then is his baptiſme, for by it as by a conduit it pleaſed God to conuay vnto vs the beſt of his fauors. For example, whereas by nature (as ſcripture ſpeakes) we were aliants fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, and ſonnes of wrath,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.3.12.</note> when wee were baptized in the name of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Sonne and holy Ghoſt, wee were brought into an holy fellowſhip with the bleſſed Trinitie, and were admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:2933:64"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="93" facs="tcp:2933:64"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="92" facs="tcp:2933:65"/>into the familie of Chriſt, euer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to remaine as adopted ſonnes in the houſe of the moſt high God; A moſt bleſſed condition.</p>
                  <p>Againe,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.1.</note> whereas by nature wee were all dead and rotten in ſinne, and altogether deuoid of the life of grace, in baptiſme wee receiued quicknance from the ſpirit of life the holie Ghoſt. And whereas our poore ſoules were beggerlie clad with natures cloath, which is (God wot) nought elſe but a torne and rotten ragge of old <hi>Adam,</hi> in baptiſme we laid aſide that old, and put on a new and moſt coſtly coate, euen the rich robe of Chriſt his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, whereby the whole Church (the ſpouſe of Chriſt) doth ſtand as a glorious obiect in the ſight of God for euermore. Laſtly, whereas by nature we were moſt filthie and loathſome in Gods eye, no leper or lazer ſo lothſome to vs as wee to God: for as the childe new borne lieth tumbling in blood, ſo we in ſin, in baptiſme we were waſhed by the cleane water of the ſpirit of God, and thereby freed from the ſpots
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:2933:65"/>and guilt of ſinne,
<note place="margin">2. King. 5.</note> as <hi>Naaman</hi> was from his leproſie in the riuer Iordan.</p>
                  <p>Thus by our baptiſme, of ſtrangers to God we became euen Gods aſſociats; of limbes of the diuell, members of Chriſt; of beggers brats poorely clad, Kings ſonnes richly attired in the righteouſnes of God; of polluted and vncleane, pure and amiable: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> thus were we bleſſed when wee were bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed with water and with the holie Ghoſt.</p>
                  <p>Now further ſee wee what great things did paſſe from vs to God in our baptiſme; ſurely as God therein became a God vnto vs, ſo wee became a people to him, wee renounced the world, and proclaimed a defiance to ſinne and Satan, wee dedicated our ſelues, ſoules and bodies to the ſeruice and worſhip of the moſt high; and as <hi>Dauid</hi> vowed to keepe Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, ſo did wee by a ſolemne vow in the ſight of men and Angels, binde our ſelues to beleeue in God, and to become as it were Gods apprentiſes, or rather the loyal ſubiects, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:2933:66"/>ſouldiers of our Lord Ieſus to fight vnder his colours, and maintaine his quarrell againſt all aduerſarie power of our ſaluation and his glorie. And thus wee ſee that in our baptiſme the Lord did great things for vs, and we promiſed great things to God againe; how requiſite a thing is it therefore, nay how neceſſary that we ſhould now and then admit of thoughts about our baptiſme, that ſo wee might haue a ſenſe and feeling of the comfort of thoſe bleſsings of God which there we receiued, and alſo be quickned vp to the carefull performance of what wee haue ſo ſolemnely promiſed. For this very cauſe I wiſh that this little trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe concerning this argument, might be as a Remembrancer to put vs in minde of theſe things which are of ſuch weight, and ſo neerely doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne vs.</p>
                  <p>As touching that other Sermon, in it wee may ſee very exactly and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciouſly handled that rare and ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar vertue ſo oft ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and called by this name, <hi>The
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:2933:66"/>feare of God,</hi> a moſt excellent gift of the ſpirit, as vſefull almoſt as any other to help forward a Chriſtian life, and no leſſe gainfull in bringing in Gods bleſsings.</p>
                  <p>As for a Chriſtian life, as we know it is chiefly ſpent in two things, that is, abſtaining from euill, and ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouring that which is good; or as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeakes, in ceaſing to doe euill,
<note place="margin">Iſaiah 1.16.17.</note> and learning to doe well. Now both theſe bee ſtreames flowing from one and the ſame ſountaine, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prou. 3.7.</note> the feare of <hi>Iehouah. Salomon</hi> ſaith, The feare of the Lord is to <hi>hate euill,</hi> Prou. <hi>8.13.</hi> there is Gods feare the cauſe of ſurceaſing from euill. He fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaith, Pron. <hi>14.2.</hi> He that wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in righteouſneſſe feareth the Lord: where the wiſe man reaſoneth from the effect to the cauſe, &amp; ſhewes that Gods feare is it that cauſeth a man to walke righteouſly, that is, to doe well: and indeed there was neuer any man that feared God, but ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured in the courſe of his life to pleaſe God in well-doing. So then as we ſee
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:2933:67"/>man that rides, in ordering his horſe doth vſe a bridle &amp; a ſpurre, a bridle to reſtraine him if hee bee too free, a ſpurre to pricke him on forward if he be dull; ſo in ordering our liues, the feare of God is as a bridle to curbe vs from ruſhing into ſin, and as a ſpurre to pricke vs on forward, and quicken our ſlow and lazie natures to that which is good and pleaſing to God.</p>
                  <p>Yet moreouer as this is a vertue of great vſe in directing vs to heauen, ſo I may truly call it, as the Apostle doth call godlineſſe, great gaine, for it brings in with it the abundance of Gods bleſsings, in ſo much as whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer will attempt to trade therewith, ſhall finde her reuenewes to bee very great: and that which <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith of Wiſedome, Prou. <hi>3.14.</hi> will be verified of her, <hi>viz.</hi> that her mercha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe is better then the merchandiſe of ſiluer, and the gaine thereof is better then gold. What good is there almost that a good man can ſet his heart a wiſhing or deſiring, but may bee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained (if God thinke meete) ſo be it
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:2933:67"/>he will be a fearer of God, the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it Pſalm. <hi>34.</hi> that nothing ſhall be wanting to them that feare him; would we liue long and inioy many daies on earth, which is the foundation of all earthly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts: the wiſe man ſaith,
<note place="margin">Prou. 10.27.</note> that the feare of the Lord increaſeth the daies. Would we faine be rich, and had in high eſteeme and repute among men? Prou. <hi>22.4.</hi> The reward of the feare of the Lord is riches, and glorie. Are wee deſirous to know the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures aright, and to bee acquainted with the deepe ſecrets and hidden councels of the moſt high God? The Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 25.14.</note> The ſecret of the Lorde is reuealed to them that feare him. Doe we long after Gods fauour, and that his louing counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance may ſhine vpon vs, without which nothing in this world is worth the hauing? The Prophet ſaith, the louing countenance of the Lord indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth for euer on them that feare him. Would we be truely happie and blest of God both in our ſelues and in our
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:2933:68"/>Children we leaue behinde vs? Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionles, our onely way for this purpoſe is to feare the Lord, Bleſſed ſaith the Prophet, Pſalm. <hi>112.1.2.</hi> is the man that feareth the Lord, his ſeede ſhall be mightie vpon earth, and the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the righteous ſhall be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. And moſt excellent is that ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, Pſalm. <hi>25.</hi> His ſoule ſhall dwell at eaſe, his children ſhall inherit the land. Loe thus and many other waies ſhall that man be bleſſed that feareth the Lord.</p>
                  <p>Thus I thought good (Right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull) to touch the titles of theſe two Sermons in theſe ſewe words, wherein you may ſee the worth and weight of the ſubiect matter they are about, and ſo be led to a further peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of them to your ſoules good.</p>
                  <p>Now the God of heauen who hath alreadie ſeaſoned your hearts with his feare, and ſet you apart as ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied veſſels to beare his glorious name, hold on your hearts in a wiſe and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous profeſsion of his truth, and grant that you may ſee your ſeruice to God
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:2933:68"/>abundantly rewarded, euen with the beſt of his fauours, vpon your ſelues, and vpon your moſt hopefull poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie for euer. From <hi>Norwich,</hi> Nouemb. <hi>15. 1613.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Worſhips true affected in all Christian loue and dutie,
<hi>Robert Gallard.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2933:69"/>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:2933:69"/>
                  <head>A SERMON, SHEWING THE FRVIT AND BENEFIT we haue by our Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>GALATH. 3.27.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>For all ye that are baptized into Chriſt, haue put on Chriſt.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Itherto the Apoſtle hath proued by the ſcope and end of the legall adminiſtration, that the law is abrogate by the comming of Chriſt: the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall law wholly, and the Morall in ſome part, <hi>viz.</hi> in reſpect of iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Now in the 26. verſe he proueth the ſame by oppoſition of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, with their former eſtate, as if hee ſhould ſay, All ye are now the ſonnes of God, you are therefore no more ſeruants, as you were vnder the law: and that they are the ſonnes of God he ſheweth it by this, that they were ingrafted into Chriſt by faith the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:2933:70"/>inſtrument of this inſition. Now in this verſe hee confirmeth this their incorporation by the teſtimonie of baptiſme, whereby the truth of this is ſigned and ſealed vnto them.</p>
                  <p>For the words themſelues, that we may with fruite be conuerſant in the handling of them, firſt let vs ſearch the true and proper meaning of them and then come to the vſe.</p>
                  <p>To be baptized into Chriſt, is to be baptized in or into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of Chriſt, that wee might be made partakers of all the benefits of Chriſt which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne ſaluation. Thus Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth it, Acts 2.38. where he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth this aduice vnto the Iews, which were touched in conſcience for their ſinne in crucifying of Chriſt, <hi>Repent &amp; be baptized in the name of the Lord Ieſus for the remiſſion of ſins.</hi> Now to be baptized into the name of Chriſt, is to haue the name of Chriſt named vpon vs, and for vs to be acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to bee his members; and by bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſine, as by a ſolemne right and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie inſtituted of God, to be inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſled and inſtalled into the familie of Chriſt, <hi>viz.</hi> his Church, and to bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with all the priuiledges thereof. This appeareth by a like phraſe vſed
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:2933:70"/>Geneſis 48.16. where <hi>Iacob</hi> at his death bleſſing <hi>Ioſephs</hi> children hath theſe words: <hi>Let my name be named on them, and the name of my fathers Abraham and Iſaack:</hi> that is, let them be all taken and reputed as my chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Now becauſe this ſpeech vſed by the Apoſtle is a ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tal phraſe, wherein that is attributed to the ſigne which is proper to the thing ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</p>
                  <p>Theſe words are further to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained on this manner: All yee that are baptized into Chriſt, that is, all ye that are ingrafted and ſet into the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of Chriſt, and haue receiued the ſacrament of Baptiſme as a ſeale and confirmation of this your inſition and incorporatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, haue put on Chriſt, euen as men doe vſe to put on a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The originall of this Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phore I take it to be this: Thoſe that were to be baptized in the Primitiue Church, being men of yeeres, were wont to put off their cloathes going into the water, and when they came out of the water either to put on new cloathes, or the old garments as new, themſelues being become new men: whereupon the Apoſtle ſpeaking of regeneration, alludeth to this cuſtom
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:2933:71"/>in two places, Epheſ. 4.22.24. Coloſſ. 3.9.10. Further, Chriſt is here com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to a garment in two reſpects: firſt in reſpect of neceſſitie; ſecondly of ornament. For the firſt, the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath this neceſſarie vſe to couer the nakedneſſe from the eyes of men, and to protect and preſerue a man from the iniuries of the ayre and the weather, <hi>viz.</hi> from the extremitie of heate and cold. In like ſort Chriſt is a couering to hide our nakednes from the ſight of God, and a ſhelter to ſhroud and defend vs from the heate and tempeſt of the wrath and anger of God: and thus is Chriſt put on in iuſtification. For the ſecond; as the garment doth adorne and beautifie a mans perſon, and doth not a little commend him and make him accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table in the preſence of men: euen ſo Chriſt being put on in faith, doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorne and inrich our ſoules with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine and ſpirituall graces, making vs to appeare precious and beautifull in the ſight of God; and thus is Chriſt put on in ſanctification: ſo then the meaning is that thoſe that by bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme are ingrafted into Chriſt, are iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified and ſanctified. And thus much ſhall ſuffice to haue ſpoken of the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:2933:71"/>meaning of the words; now come we to the vſe: the which is manifold.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, if baptiſme be a ſacrament of our incorporation into Chriſt, our dutie is to labour by all meanes in truth and indeed to be ſet into Chriſt and to be made members of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, that ſo we may anſwere our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion made in baptiſme. Great is the careleſnes of the world in this point: all men that liue and are borne in the Church, haue this benefit vouchſafed them in the beginning of their daies, to bee brought into the Church by baptiſme, and to be acknowledged as true members thereof, but few there are that labour for the inward bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, repreſented and ſealed by the outward, to wit, to become the liuelie me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of that myſtical body, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Chriſt is the head. I will therefore vſe ſome reaſons as motiues, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce and perſwade vs to become members of Chriſt: the firſt whereof is this.</p>
                  <p>God of his infinite mercy and loue in Ieſus Chriſt hath vouchſafed vs this honour in the beginning of our daies, (when we were no members of Chriſt actually, but children of wrath and heires of damnation) to call vs by
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:2933:72"/>his owne name, ſetting (as it were) the ſtampe and ſeale of baptiſme vpon vs, thereby as by a badge &amp; cognizance not onely acknowledging vs for his, but diſtinguiſhing vs from the pagan, infidell and prophane companie of men in the world, thereby alſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnely admitting vs into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church, and endowing vs with all the priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges thereof: if wee will not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bee wilfull contemners and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſers of ſo great grace, and on our parts, as much as in vs lieth, make fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the holy ordinance of God, and preiudice that good which he meant and offered vnto vs in baptiſme, let vs labour to be ſet and ingrafted into Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, as it is no ſmall priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge for a man to be acknowledged for a member of this Church, and of Chriſt before hee bee; ſo is it a farre greater prerogatiue truly to bee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted into him. Why ſo? becauſe by this meanes thou haſt fellowſhip and communion with Chriſt, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as he is man, but as he is God, and the ſecond perſon in Trinitie, and by reaſon of him, with the Father and the holy Ghoſt: Now what a prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and preheminence is this for a
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:2933:72"/>man, being but duſt and aſhes, yea a worme creeping and groueling vpon the earth, to haue communion with the moſt great and glorious God, who is King and Lord of heauen and earth?</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, this incorporation is the ground and foundation of all thoſe benefits we haue in Chriſt: for hence it is that whole Chriſt is made ours, both in iuſtification &amp; ſanctification: 1. Cor. 1.30. <hi>He of God is made vnto vs wiſedome, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fourthly, hence it is that wee haue title and intereſt vnto eternal life, and are heires and fellow-heires with Chriſt of his kingdome, and ſhall as Kings reigne with him in glorie for euer after this life.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, the very conſideration of our miſerable eſtate by nature ought to prick vs forward, and euen to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine vs hereunto, which is this: The image of God is defaced and almoſt raced out in vs, and wee are vile and deformed creatures in the ſight of God, more loathſome and odious vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, then the dogge or toade is or can be to vs; in our mindes full of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and error, in our wils of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumacie and rebellion, in our affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:2933:73"/>of diſorder, being alwaies prone to euill, &amp; neuer to that which is good; in our conſciences of guilti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and in our memories of forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, in our words and deeds of mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold offences, in the whole man wee are fearfully thrall and in bondage to ſinne and Satan, and vnto theſe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions and ſinnes the puniſhment is anſwerable: for in our mindes wee are ſubiect to frenzies and madneſſe in our conſciences to horrours and ſtrange feares, in our bodies to aches, innumerable diſeaſes and infirmities, in our goods to loſſes, &amp; in our names to ignominie and contempt, in the end of this life to death, and in the life to come to the ſecond death, which is a ſeparation of the whole man from the preſence of God: If then this be the ſtate of euery man till he be in Chriſt, how doth it ſtand vs vpon to labour in this point aboue al things, that we may be true members of Chriſt? And that we may be incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate into the bodie of Chriſt, three things muſt be practiſed.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, wee muſt acknowledge our ſelues to bee no members of Chriſt, but limmes of the Diuell, vaſſals and bondſlaues of Satan, firebrands of
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:2933:73"/>hell, and members of the kingdome of darkneſſe, alienates and ſtrangers from the Couenant and Church of God. In the third of <hi>Matthew</hi> none were baptized of <hi>Iohn,</hi> but ſuch as confeſſed their ſinnes.</p>
                  <p>We muſt in the next place be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, that is, bee heartily grieued and diſpleaſed with our ſelues for our ſinnes, purpoſing and reſoluing by Gods grace neuer to returne to the practiſe of them, but hence forward to liue in newneſſe of life: For this cauſe <hi>Iohns</hi> baptiſme, Mark. 1.4. is called the baptiſme of repentance, becauſe of the parties baptized (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men of yeares) was required a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification of their repentance, and their baptiſme was a ſolemne profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion thereof.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, we muſt with humble and contrite hearts come vnto Chriſt; firſt, beginning to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of the Goſpell; then to hunger and thirſt after them; and laſt of all, by faith to embrace and lay hold of them, Matth. 11.28. But how may we come to Chriſt? only by faith: for ſo, beleeuing and comming vnto Chriſt are put one for another, Ioh. 6.35. For faith is the foote which carrieth and
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:2933:74"/>bringeth vs vnto Chriſt, and being come to him, it is the hand whereby we receiue Chriſt, &amp; the bond where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wee are coupled vnto him, and made one with him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                     </label> If faith bee required to our ingraf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting into Chriſt, to what vſe ſerueth baptiſme to Infants? who wanting actuall faith cannot be implanted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt, and therefore this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can bee no ſeale vnto them of their incorporation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Solution. </seg>
                     </label> Infants borne in the Church are of two ſort; ſome reprobate, ſome elect. The former howſoeuer they haue the outward element conferred vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and are charitablie reputed of the Church to appertaine vnto the Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, (it leauing ſecret iudgements vnto God) yet before God they are not in the Couenant: and therefore baptiſme though in it ſelfe it bee the ſacrament of incorporation, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the inſtitution of Chriſt, yet to them it is not, but becomes altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnprofitable, and turneth to their greater iudgement and condemnâ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by reaſon of their abuſe &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanation of the holy ordinance of God. Elect Infants are alſo of two ſorts; ſome die in their infancie, ſome
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:2933:74"/>liue till they come to the yeares of diſcretion: as for the former they are ingrafted into Chriſt, not by any faith, (which they haue not, neither indeede can haue by reaſon of their age) but by a ſecret and vnſpeakable working of the holy Ghoſt, vniting and coupling them vnto Chriſt, and applying vnto them the perfect o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of Chriſt for their iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from original ſinne, and inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly renewing them in the inward man, and repairing the image of God in them in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe: for the latter wherof there is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter queſtion; Baptiſme hath this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vſe in them, it is a ſymball, and (as it were) a doore of their ſolemne entrance &amp; admiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into the Church of God, and for the time to come it is a ſeale and pledge vnto them of their certaine incorporation into the body of Chriſt. Thus much of the firſt vſe.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, if by baptiſme wee are ingrafted into Chriſt, then let vs walk as it becommeth the members of Chriſt. 2. Cor. 5.17. <hi>If any man be in Chriſt, let him be a new creature,</hi> that is, renewed in his minde, in his thoughts, in his purpoſes, in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, in his affections, in his ſpeeches,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:2933:75"/>in his actions and whole conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; let none of theſe ſauour of the fleſh, but of the ſpirit: and why ſo? becauſe <hi>All old things</hi> (ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) <hi>are paſt, and all things are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come new:</hi> So likewiſe Galath. 5.25. <hi>If we liue in the ſpirit,</hi> that is, if being coupled vnto Chriſt, we be quickned by his ſpirit in the inward man, then <hi>let vs walke in the ſpirit,</hi> that is, let vs bring foorth the fruites, and doe the workes of the ſpirit, and not of the fleſh. If a man were called out of the countrie to liue in the citie, and made one of the corporation, his name be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing regiſtred in the Roles, and he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>franchiſed and entitled to all the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges of a free Citizen, he would ſhake off all his rude and ruſticall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiours, and carry himſelfe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe ciuilly as a Citizen: ſo likewiſe wee being called out of this world, that is, the corrupt ſtock of mankind, and ſet into Chriſt the true vine, our dutie is to caſt off all our worldly and carnall behauiours, and to carrie and demeane our ſelues honeſtly, as it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth the members of Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now made (as it were) free Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of the kingdome of heauen.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, if by baptiſme we are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:2933:75"/>into Chriſt, let vs endeuour and vſe al good meanes daily to grow vp more and more with him in this ſpirituall coniunction. The members of the naturall bodie at the firſt are but ſmall and ſlender, but ſtill they grow in ſtrength and receiue daily increaſe, till they come to their iuſt quantitie: euen ſo it is in the myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call body of Chriſt, though at the firſt we be but babes in Chriſt, yet by the continuall vſe of the Word and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, and by prayer, meditation, &amp;c. wee muſt looke to receiue conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual increaſe, growing from grace to grace till we come to be tall &amp; ſtrong men in Chriſt Ieſus. The ſience or graffe that is ſet into a ſtocke and doth not proſper and grow greater, neither bearing leafe, nor bringing foorth fruite, we iudge it to be a dead and a rotten branch, and that worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and that it liueth not by the ſappe and iuyce of the roote; ſemblablie, when as by baptiſme wee are ſet into Chriſt, and make no progreſſe or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in knowledge, in faith, in loue, in zeale, in godlineſſe, in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, it is an argument wee are but dead branches, and are but only out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly in appearance before men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:2933:76"/>into Chriſt, and not truly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed before God.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, here al parents are taught their dutie, as the common care of all is (which is commendable) by bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme to bring their children into the Church, ſo when they come to yeeres (which is commonly neglected of al) to inſtruct them touching the matter and vſe of baptiſme, a maine &amp; prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall point whereof is their infition into Chriſt, labouring to bring them to the ſight and ſenſe of their ſinnes, to repentance vnfained for the ſame, and conſequently by the vſe of the Word and Sacraments to true fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip and communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, heere is a matter of great comfort vnto all that are fallen, or by infirmitie, or otherwiſe haue made relapſe in ſome or more grieuous ſinnes: for when a man fallen ſhall conſider that baptiſme is a ſigne and ſeale of our perpetuall inſition, and indiſſoluble vnion with Chriſt, in which is granted a generall pardon of all ſins paſt, preſent and to come, neuer to be repealed, becauſe the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant remaineth euer in force vnto them that repent and obſerue the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. Eſay 54.10. <hi>The couenant of
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:2933:76"/>my peace ſhall not faile:</hi> he taketh hart and comforteth himſelf in hope of fauour and mercie, if he returne vnto God by repentance. For baptiſme is like vnto a ſhip, out of which if a man ſhall be fallen into the Sea, and ſhall but catch hold of a board to bring him to the ſhip, the Pylot will be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to receiue him: ſo if a man ſhall after his fall (hauing caught the board of repentance) returne vnto bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, the Lord will be readie to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue him to mercie, and it will bee of force to ſaue him.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, if baptiſme bee the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our incorporation, then wee ought to honour it, to reuerence and regard it as the holie ordinance of God, and by all meanes to teſtifie the ſame. And heere a common abuſe commeth to be taxed and reproued, when men depart foorth of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation in the time of adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, thereby manifeſting their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the holy Sacrament, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as by their preſence and decent beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour they ought to teſtifie their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence vnto the ordinance of God, and their ioy for the adding of a member vnto the Church.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Haue put on Chriſt.</hi> Chriſt is put
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:2933:77"/>on three waies. Firſt in his merit: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly in his efficacie, and thirdly in his example. For the firſt, Chriſt is put on in his merit, when as by faith his righteouſneſſe and meritorious obedience is applied vnto iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſaluation: this is ſigned and ſealed by the action of the Miniſter beſprinkling the bodie of the partie baptized with water, thereby repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting the blood of Chriſt, which being ſprinkled vpon the ſoule by the hand of faith, purgeth and cleanſeth it from all ſinne, 1. Ioh. 1.7. Our dutie therfore which we learne from hence is this; that we are to labour aboue all things to bee purged and waſhed in our conſciences from ſinne, that our hearts being purified by faith, wee might ſtand blameleſſe and without fault before God. Acts 22.16. <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias</hi> is brought in giuing this coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell vnto <hi>Paul; Ariſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and be baptized, &amp; waſh away thy ſins,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Chriſt is put on in his ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacie, when as by the vertue and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of his death a man killeth and crucifieth the corruption of his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and by the power of his reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection he reuiueth and is raiſed out of the graue of his ſinne, to holineſſe
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:2933:77"/>and newnes of life: this is alſo ſigned and ſealed in our baptiſme, and for that cauſe we are ſaid, Rom. 6.3. to be baptized into the death of Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe baptiſme is the ſeale and ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our mortification: neither of that only but of our viuification alſo, as may appeare Rom. 6.4. for we muſt be like faſhioned vnto Chriſt, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the ſimilitude of his death, that as he died for our ſinnes, ſo we by the vertue of the ſame death ſhould die vnto ſinne, but alſo in the ſimilitude of his reſurrection, that as hee roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine for our iuſtification, ſo wee by the vertue of the ſame ſhould riſe out of ſinne vnto righteouſneſſe and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe of life. Our dutie is therefore to labour for ſpirituall regeneration, for ſo baptiſme is termed by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, Titus 3.5. <hi>the lauer of the new birth, and renewing of the holy Ghost.</hi> Hereunto <hi>Paul</hi> exhorteth, Epheſ. 4.22.24. and Phil. 3.9.10. alluding vnto baptiſme.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, Chriſt is put on in his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, when hee is made a paterne of all morall duties wherein hee hath gone before vs for imitation. Our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is here to denie our ſelues, to take vp our croſſe and follow Chriſt in his
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:2933:78"/>patience, in his meeknes, in his humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, in his loue, in his obedience: And vnto this putting on of Chriſt the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle exhorteth, Colloſſ. 3.12.13.14. Now vnto this putting on of Chriſt in that manner, which I haue ſaid, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers and ſundrie reaſons and induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments may bee brought: the firſt is this.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt is here compared to a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which argueth that our naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and filthineſſe is apparent in the ſight of God, before it bee couered therewith, and wee alſo expoſed to all the plagues and iudgements of God: If wee would therefore haue aſſurance of our iuſtification before God, and our acceptation of him vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to fauour and mercie, and our free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome &amp; deliuerance from the wrath and anger of God, let vs labour to put on Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, in the knitting of theſe two together, our inſition into Chriſt with our putting on of Chriſt: we ſee that all that are truly ingraſted into Chriſt, they are iuſtified, ſanctified, and walke in obedience vnto God. If therefore we would haue any teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie or argument to perſwade vs, that wee are in Chriſt, wee muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:2933:78"/>put on Chriſt, for here theſe twaine are inſeparably coupled to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the Apoſtle.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, if wee ſhall not thus put on Chriſt wee are not in him, and conſequently baptiſme is vnto vs a nullitie and becommeth of none ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: for it is but as a ſeale ſet to a blanke,
<note place="margin">Rom. 2.35.</note> the Apoſtle ſaith <hi>Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion verily prafiteth, &amp;c.</hi> But if thou be a tranſgreſſour of the law, thy cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion is made vncircumciſion; ſo baptiſme loſeth his grace in them that are not regenerate.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, the conſideration of our vow and promiſe ſo ſolemnely made in baptiſme touching the renouncing of the Diuell, the world, the fleſh, and the embracing and following of Chriſt and his truth ought to moue vs hereunto, vnleſſe wee will become truce-breakers with God, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temners of the couenant, vnto which wee are intitled in the beginning of our daies. Neither may wee pleaſe our ſelues in an outward profeſſion that wee haue giuen vp our names vnto God in baptiſme, and are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged to be his, and liue in the Church, comming to heare Sermons, and to receiue the Sacraments at
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:2933:79"/>times appointed, but wee muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede further to anſwere in truth and in deede vnto our profeſſion made in baptiſme: for it is not the waſhing of the filth of the fleſh by the mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall element of water that doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend vs vnto God, but the ſtipu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of a good conſcience ſanctified and purged by the blood of Chriſt.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:2933:79"/>
                  <head>A SERMON, WHEREIN IS DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared the nature of the feare of God.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>PROV. 1.7.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>The feare of Iehouah is the beginning of wiſedome.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O omit the coherence of theſe words with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, becauſe it maketh not much for the further vnderſtanding or opening of this place, the words in themſelues con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine a briefe or ſumme of all that doctrine, and the ground of all thoſe exhortations which are propounded in the 9. firſt Chapters of this booke: which is this, that the reuerence of <hi>Iehouah</hi> is the chiefe wiſedome, and the gate or entrance to all wiſedome, according to which whoſoeuer doth order and frame his life, may be iuſtly called a wiſe man. In the words is contained a deſcription of the feare of God by a double argument. The
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:2933:80"/>firſt is taken from the ſubiect, to wit, <hi>Iehouah,</hi> for about his Maieſtie is this feare conuerſant. The ſecond taken from the nature of it, to wit, it is the principall wiſedom, or the very foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and headſpring of all true wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
                  <p>For the better vnderſtanding of the words, wee muſt remember that there is a three-fold feare mentioned in Scripture. The firſt is a naturall feare, which is occupied about ſome imminent euill and danger, which may either deſtroy, or grieue and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noy the creature; ſo our Sauiour Chriſt feared death. The ſecond is a diſtruſtfull feare, euery where diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended in Scripture and diſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, as 1. Ioh. 4. perfect loue ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth out this feare of incredulitie. The third is a feare proceeding from faith as a fruite of it, in which ſenſe we are to ſpeake of it in this place, being that which here is commended vnto vs: this is called the feate of <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But here it will be demanded how God can be the obiect of feare, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that feare is occupied about ſome future euill, and that not farre off, but imminent and neere at hand;
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:2933:80"/>and no ſmall euill, but ſo great as that a man is not able by his power either to reſiſt, or to ſuſtaine and ouercome it. Now God is goodneſſe it ſelfe, yea the chiefeſt good to bee deſired and earneſtly ſought after of all, and therefore to be feared of none. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwera.</hi> The proper and direct obiect of feare is ſome euill, yet indirectly, and in the ſecond place it reſpecteth the partie or perſon from whence the euill commeth; as hope firſt of all reſpecteth the good thing hoped for and next, the perſon of whom this good thing is to be receiued ſo the moſt direct and proper obiect of this feare is the diſpleaſure of God, which is the onely euill to be feared and auoided of all men; and more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>directly and in the ſecond place it is referred to God himſelf, and called the feare of <hi>Iehouah.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This feare proceeding from faith is ſaid to be the chiefeſt wiſedom, both becauſe from hence us from a pure fountaine proceedeth all true wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: and herein alſo conſiſteth the greateſt part of ſpirituall and diuine wiſedome to reuerence the true God.</p>
                  <p>Touching this feare, that we may with fruite conſider and entreare of
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:2933:81"/>it, foure things are to be learned: firſt what it is; ſecondly, by what markes and notes it is knowne and diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: thirdly, by what meanes it is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained and kept: fourthly, by what arguments wee are to be induced to ſeeke after it and practiſe it. For the firſt, to begin with the acception and vſe of the word, which in Scripture is manifold. Firſt, it is put for God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: Geneſ. 31.53. <hi>Iaakob</hi> ſware by the feare of his father <hi>Izhak.</hi> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for his word and doctrine, Pſal. 19.9. The feare of the Lord is cleare, &amp;c. Thirdly, generally for the whole wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, Pſalm. 34.9. Ionah. 1.9. Fourthly, it is put for a ſpeciall part of Gods worſhip, and ſignifieth this chaſt &amp; filiall feare, that feare where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the wife feareth the husband, and the childe the father; which may bee thus deſcribed. It is a peculiar gift of the holie Ghoſt in the regenerate, whereby a man, being reſolued parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly and effectually of Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, ſtandeth in awe to diſpleaſe him, and endeuoureth to pleaſe him in all things.</p>
                  <p>Firſt it is a gift, Eſay 11.2. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is a peculiar gift to diſtinguiſh it from the common gifts of the Spirit,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:2933:81"/>as Prophecie, which is a gift to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prete and expound Scripture; illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; a gift to practiſe a particular calling; a gift to bridle and moderate the affections; and temporarie faith: all which, with many others, bee in reprobates, and ſuch as are deſtitute of the feare of God.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, in the regenerate: and that is added for two cauſes: firſt, becauſe vnregenerate and wicked men that liue in their ſinnes doe want this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly feare, Rom. 3.18. Pſalm. 36.1. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, to diſtinguiſh it from that feare which is in them. Now the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference conſiſteth in theſe 3. things:</p>
                  <p>Firſt, the feare of the godly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from faith and loue of God, for he beleeueth euery word of God: The commanding word, and therfore feareth to tranſgreſſe euen becauſe of the authoritie of the commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: The promiſing word, and therefore feareth leſt through vnthankfulneſſe and diſobedience hee ſhould depriue himſelfe of the vſe and fruite of the promiſe: and the threatning word, and therefore feareth leſt hee ſhould incurre the danger of Gods wrath, &amp; curſe denounced againſt the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of his law. Againe, becauſe hee
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:2933:82"/>loueth God, therefore hee feareth to offend him, and by ſinne to diuide and ſeparate himſelfe from him. Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riwiſe, the feare of the wicked pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from diſtruſt, for he only ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting before him the conſideration of the curſe, the iudgements of God due vnto him, hell, death, and damnation, vtterly deſpaireth of mercie, and his conſcience, by the aſſiſtance of the holy Ghoſt, applying the curſe, is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerwhelmed with exceſſiue feare, and plunged into the gulfe of deſperation and deſtruction. Againe, it procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth of corrupt ſelfeloue, whereby he loueth his owne welfare, his preſent and future good eſtate, his own plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and luſts, and abhorreth euery thing that may croſſe him in them. Laſtly, of the hatred of God; for this is his damnable diſpoſition that hee wiſheth there were no God, the law were no law, ſinne were not ſinne, that he might ſtill liue in the practiſe of his luſts without checke or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trolement.</p>
                  <p>They differe in the obiect:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The feare of the godly is conuerſant about <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum culpae,</hi> and the offence of Gods Maieſtie principally, holding that to be the greateſt euill: and leſſe princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:2933:82"/>and in the ſecond place, about the <hi>malum paena,</hi> and Gods wrath: for this is the ingenuus diſpoſition of the childe of God, that though there were no hell or puniſhment for euill doers, yet would he ſhun and auoide ſinne for it ſelfe, becauſe God abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it. The feare of the wicked is oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied about <hi>malu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paenae</hi> alone, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is indeede a ſeruile and ſlauiſh feare, and if there were no puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for ſinne he would neuer feare, and the more he is puniſhed the more he rebelleth.</p>
                  <p>In the effect:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the former cauſeth a man to goe vnto God, and to ſecke comfort from him alone, yea though he ſhew himſelfe an enemie, and as it were a perſecutor in all reaſon, as to <hi>Iob:</hi> the latter cauſeth a man to flie from God, and to runne away from him, and to fret and fume againſt him; and in one word, the one hath hope of comfort with it, the other hath none. The difference further may bee illuſtrated by this compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: The feare of the godly is like the feare of the chaſt Matrone, who fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth her husband being preſent leſt hee ſhould depart from her, leſt hee ſhould diminiſh his affectionate loue
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:2933:83"/>toward her, and by any offence on her part haue his minde alienated from her: Contrariwiſe, the feare of the wicked is like to that of the ſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet and adulterous wife, who feareth her husband abſent, leſt he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, and preſent, leſt hee ſhould know and be made priuie to her wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and vnchaſt practiſes.</p>
                  <p>Whereby a man being reſolued particularly, &amp;c. This reſolution is the ground of the feare of God: now it neceſſarily preſuppoſeth an apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or conceiuing of God in the minde; which how it may be, (ſeeing God is infinit and incomprehenſible, and therefore cannot bee compaſſed within the narrow &amp; ſtaight bounds of humane reaſon and capacitie) it may be demanded.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> God is not conceiued of vs as he is in his owne nature, neither yet by negation, or analogie, but as be hath reuealed himſelfe in his word and creatures. God hath reuealed himſelfe in his word to be holy, wiſe, good, iuſt, mercifull, infinite, omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent: therfore the minde of man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth him to be holy, &amp;c. God hath reuealed himſelfe in his creatures to be great, mightie, terrible, a God full
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:2933:83"/>of power, glorie, and Maieſtie: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the minde of man conceiueth him to be ſo. This apprehenſion bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth a reſolution of Gods preſence in the minde; but vnleſſe it be further ſetled in the heart and conſcience it is vnprofitable: and therefore I adde it muſt bee particular: not onely that whereby a man is perſwaded gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally that God ſeeth and knoweth all things, and is preſent at all mens ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but alſo effectually, ſuch as ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the heart with an holy reuerence in regard of Gods Maieſtie. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of there be two effects: firſt an awe,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> which is two-fold: Firſt in reſpect of ſinne, whereunto <hi>Dauid</hi> exhorteth <hi>Sauls</hi> Courtiers, Pſal. 4.4. An exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple whereof wee haue in <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> who being ſollicited vnto folly by <hi>Poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phars</hi> wife, was hereby reſtrained, Geneſ. 19.9. Secondly, in regard of puniſhment or chaſtiſement, either preſent, whereunto <hi>Peter</hi> exhorteth, 1. Pet. 5.6. Examples whereof wee haue in <hi>Ely,</hi> 1. Sam. 3.18. and in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> 2. Sam. 16.10. Pſal. 39.9. and in <hi>Iob, Iob</hi> 1.21. Or future, when a man feareth to ſin becauſe of Gods threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, which euen the childe of God ought to dread: for the naturall child
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:2933:84"/>feareth not only the offence of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but euen the rod alſo and whip. But is not this a ſeruile feare? No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſe: this feare is good, and a part of that filiall feare whereby wee worſhip God in this life, as appeareth by theſe reaſons. Firſt, it is the gift of God, Eſay 11.2. Ierem. 32.40. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, it is commended vnto vs in Scripture; both by precept, Leuit. 19.14. which is a morall precept, and Matth. 10.28. and by practiſe; in the example of <hi>Iehoſhaphat,</hi> 2. Chron. 20.3. of <hi>Ioſias,</hi> 2. King. 21.13. in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Habakkuk. Hab.</hi> 3.16. in <hi>Dauid,</hi> Pſal. 119.120. in <hi>Iob, Iob.</hi> 31.23. and in Chriſt: who though hee naturally feared death, yet had a further feare by reaſon of the horrible wrath of God to bee ſuſtained for the ſinne of man: and therefore the Apoſtle ſaith, Hebr. 5.7. that hee was heard in that which hee feared. Thirdly, it is a meanes to eſcape the wrath of God, as ye may ſee, Hab. 3.16. Fourthly, it becommeth not vs to be ſecure when God ſhewes himſelfe to bee terrible and fearefull in his workes or iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. And if God be to be feared, why not his wrath? and if hee would haue vs to feare the ſword of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:2933:84"/>why not his owne? conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that the ſword of the Magiſtrate is his owne ſword. And why doth God threaten ſo many plagues euen to his children, but to this end that they might feare them? And if it diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe God that we are ſenſeleſſe, and not grieued and moued when hee doth afflict vs, Ierem. 5.3. doth it not alſo diſpleaſe him that wee doe not feare when he threatneth? Yea what father or perſon in authoritie aboue other is there among men, that doth not loue to haue his threats feared of his children and inferiours? Fifthly, this feare is very many waies profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and neceſſarie: for firſt it expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the contempt of God and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie of the fleſh, euen in the rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate, and makes them tractable and pliable, and prompt to doe the will of God: and hence it is that the Lord doth often exerciſe his children with legall terrors and feares, that they might bee the more humbled, and ſo made the more willing to obey. An example of this we haue in <hi>Paul,</hi> who by reaſon of thoſe feares in his firſt conuerſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wherwith he was ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſmitten and aſtonied, was greatly caſt downe, and became farre more
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:2933:85"/>prompt to obey God. And this is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the contrarie: for what is the cauſe why Atheiſts, Epicures, and prophane wretches, doe ſinne with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all ſhame and regard of common honeſtie? but that they haue caſt out of their hearts all feare of God, and al conſideration of his iudgements, that they might more freely without all checke wallow in the mire of their carnall pleaſures, and bathe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh themſelues in their vile and beaſtly ſinnes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond effect is an endeucur to pleaſe him: To this the Lord exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <hi>Abraham,</hi> Geneſ. 17.1. and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples hereof we haue in <hi>Enoch,</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſ. 3. and <hi>Noah,</hi> Geneſ. 6. who both of them receiued this teſtimonie that they walked with God: that is, as in his preſence. For when a man conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth that God ſeeth his heart, and knoweth all his thoughts, then hee laboureth to auoide diſſembling, and to be vpright. The vſe of this ſerueth to condemne the practiſe of moſt men: for who almoſt is perſwaded of Gods preſence? God ſeeth vs, but we doe not eſpie him: who ſtandeth in awe of him, but vpon euery occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion yeeldeth vnto ſinne? who is pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient?
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:2933:85"/>who ſtudieth to pleaſe &amp; glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God? howſoeuer many profeſſe the ſame outwardly.</p>
                  <p>Now that we may not deceiue our ſelues in this matter, there be certaine markes whereby this true feare of God may bee diſcerned: which bee theſe.</p>
                  <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> when a man ſetteth himſelfe in Gods preſence, whereſoeuer hee become, or whatſoeuer hee is about, after the example of <hi>Danid,</hi> Pſal. 16.8 whereof follow many notable effects.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, if a man bee in companie hee will obſerue and vſe the opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of doing and receiuing good: if he ſpeake, he will ſpeake wiſely, and guide his words with diſcretion, or elſe be ſilent: yea he will obſerue the occaſions and ſeaſons of ſpeaking and keeping ſilence, and his outward car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage will be graue, moderate, decent, ſober; not only inoffenſiue, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to edification. If hee be to doe any part of Gods worſhip either pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate or publike, hee will doe it with reuerence, with care to glorifie God, to profit others and himſelfe: if he be about any worke of his calling, hee wil doe it faithfully, ſincerely, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently: if about any morall duty of
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:2933:86"/>loue vnto men, hee will performe it willingly, and cheerefully, and in an holy manner.</p>
                  <p>To make conſcience of all ſinne,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Prou. 14.16 and of moral obedience. Now to make conſcience of ſinne, is, when a man in conſideration of Gods preſence and commandement, abſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth from ſinne euen then when he is ſtrongly tempted thereunto: as <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> did: for otherwiſe not euery ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaining from ſin is by and by a ſigne of the true feare of God. But to this three things be required: firſt, a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly iealouſie and ſuſpition ouer a mans ſelfe, leſt by ſinne he ſhould fall from God: and good reaſon, becauſe of that domeſticall and inbred enemie of deceit, which is deepely fixed in euery mans heart by nature, Iere. 17.9 Secondly, a continuall care and watchfulnes ouer the heart and life, and ouer all the members of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and the ſenſes, that they be no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments either to occaſion or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, or to execute ſinne, commended vnto vs, Prou. 4.23. Thirdly, a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> only to foreſee the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and deceits of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>all enemie, and carefully to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent them; but to furniſh a man with
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:2933:86"/>ſpirituall armour out of the word of God againſt all aſſayes. Againe, a man muſt make conſcience not onely of outward publick ſinnes, whereof the world crieth ſhame: but of ſecret ſins which he might commit without the knowledge of any; yea, of the inward and ſecret conceits of the heart, as <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi> who might haue done the euill to which he was ſollicited ſecretly, ſo that no man ſhould haue knowne it, but euen then the feare of God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held him. So alſo Prou. 8.13. Iob 31.23. Againe, there is this conſcience of morall obedience: for theſe two be alwaies coupled together: Eccleſ. 12.13. Pro. 14.2. Pſal. 112.1. Acts 10.35.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> To feare at the hearing of Gods iudgements threatned in his word, or executed in the world. Eſay 66.5. Heare the word of God, yee that tremble at his word. And the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Habakkuk</hi> 3.16. ſaid, that when he heard Gods threatnings, hee feared, and his belly trembled, and rottenneſſe entered into his bones, and hee was wonderfully diſmaied and terrified. And to bee ſilent and wonder at the remembrance of the iudgements of God, as did <hi>Aaron,</hi> who held his peace when his two
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:2933:87"/>ſons were deſtroyed by fire from the Lord, Leu. 10.3. and to be prouoked by them to repentance, which is the right vſe of al his iudgments, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reall ſermons, which vſe our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our teacheth vs, Luk. 13.3.</p>
                  <p>To feare God more then men:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> that is, to be more afraid of the diſpleaſure of God then of men; and therefore to preferre obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vnto his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements before mans, as did the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew Midwiues, Exod. 1.17. and the Apoſtles, Acts 5.29. and to dread more the ſhame which God ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bring vpon vs, then the ſhame of men: for the ſhame of men is but loſſe of cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit and good name, whereas the other is euerlaſting confuſion. Let no man therfore be afraid in the cauſe of God and of religion to vndergoe ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, for ſuch a one the Lord honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth. Contrariwiſe, if he be aſhamed to profeſſe Chriſt heere, then let him know hee is deſtitute of the feare of God, and Chriſt will bee aſhamed of him.</p>
                  <p>Humilitie:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> for theſe two are ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned together, and haue one reward aſſigned vnto them, Prou. 22.4. the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of humilitie, and of the feare of God is riches, glory and life.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="137" facs="tcp:2933:87"/>
Deſire of knowledge: theſe two 6.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> are alſo combined, Eſay 11.2. and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as the naturall child is deſirous to know his fathers will that he migh o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey it, and pleaſe him, leſt happily hee might through ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce tranſgreſſe; euen ſo the true feare of God carrieth with it deſire and endeuour to know his will and commandements.</p>
                  <p>Hauing ſhewed both what this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly feare is, and which bee the markes and ſignes thereof, it followeth now that wee ſpeake of the third generall things propounded, namelie, the meanes of obtaining this grace, and of bringing our harts vnto a true feare of God: which be theſe.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, meditation and ſerious conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of God, and that, firſt of his authoritie, rule, and abſolute domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion ouer all things, which ought to ſtrike a reuerence into all; euen as Princes, Magiſtrates, and Superiours, are feared for their authority. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of the glorie, maieſtie, and ſublimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of God, who is aboue al creatures: nay, in whoſe preſence the Angels are not pure, Eſay 6.2. and the Sunne is darkenes, and at whoſe becke all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are ſubiect as his hoaſt and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, to execute his will. Thirdly, the
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:2933:88"/>baſenes of man, both in reſpect of his weakenes, (who is not able to ſtand before God and to behold his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, no more then the brittle glaſſe to hold ſtrong liquour: and therfore the Apoſtle ſaith that fleſh and blood cannot inherit the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and that this corruptible muſt put on incorruption before it can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into glorie) and as alſo in regard of ſin, the conſcience and guilt wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of maketh a man afraid, and aſhamed to come neere to God, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in <hi>Adam,</hi> Geneſ. 3. who after his fall, being aſhamed of Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, ſewed fig tree leaues together and made aprons to couer his naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and if it were poſſible to hide it from God. And <hi>Moſes</hi> Exod. 3.6. and <hi>Peter,</hi> Luk. 5.8. Fourthly, of the om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotencie of God, who is able euen with the breath of his noſthrils to conſume and bring to nought all that rebell againſt him. Fifthly, of his iuſtice, iudgements, and mercie. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of his omnipreſence, and of his omniſcience.</p>
                  <p>Secondly; earneſt prayer for this grace eſpecially: for that is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duit pipe to conuey this and all other graces into the hearts of Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:2933:88"/>
                     <hi>Dauid</hi> praied for this grace par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, Pſal. 86.11. and God gaue it him; for he teſtifieth of himſelfe that his fleſh trembled for feare of Gods iudgements. God hath alſo promiſed to beſtow it vpon his children, <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie</hi> 32.40.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, the deniall of our ſelues, eſpecially of our fleſhly wiſedome. Prou. 3.7. <hi>Be not wiſe in thine owne eyes: feare the Lord, and depart from euill.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Come we now to the fourth point, which is the motiues whereby wee may be perſwaded to ſeeke after this heauenly grace: and they be theſe.</p>
                  <p>Firſt the commandement of God: which wee haue in many places of Scripture, and among others in theſe: Eccleſ. 12.13. Pſal. 34.9. Secondly, the examples of holy men that haue herein gone before vs, as of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> Gen. 22.12. of <hi>Iacob,</hi> and <hi>Izhak.</hi> Geneſ. 31.42. and 53. of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſ. 39.9. of <hi>Dauid,</hi> 1. Chron. 13 12. of <hi>Iob,</hi> 1.1. of <hi>Simeon,</hi> Luke 2.25. of <hi>Cornelius,</hi> Acts 10.2.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, the large promiſes which God hath made to this grace, of good things both ſpirituall and temporall. Firſt ſpirituall bleſſings, and they are
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:2933:89"/>many: as firſt illumination and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the ſcriptures, Pſal. 25.14. Then obedience, and grace to liue well, Pſal. 25.12. The loue and fauour of God, Pſal. 103.17. life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, Prou. 22.4. Prou. 19.23. and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, Pſal. 112.1. Prou. 28.14. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, for temporall good things: God hath promiſed to them that feare him proſperitie, Pſal. 34.9.10. Pſal. 112.3. Glorie and honour, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbs 22.4. A good condition of life, together with the continuance of the ſame, and immunitie from euill, Prou. 19.23. long life on earth and length of daies, Prou. 10.27. The bleſſing of children and poſteritie, Pſal. 112.2. Pſalme 25.13. Protection from dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, Pſal. 33.18.19. All which good promiſes haue bin fulfilled in <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Dauid,</hi> and their poſteritie. And if at any time theſe temporall promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are not performed vnto vs, yet is not God falſe of his word, becauſe theſe promiſes and the like muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies be vnderſtood with the excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the croſſe. Yea in one word, God hath promiſed to them which haue this grace, all good things both temporal and ſpiritual; as Pſal. 25.13. His ſoule ſhall dwell at eaſe; that is,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:2933:89"/>be repleniſhed with all bleſſings.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, let vs remember the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great profits and commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which attend vpon this feare of God: It teacheth a man to obſerue the golden rule of mediocrity in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry eſtate of life, Eccleſ. 7.20.21. It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraineth and hindreth vs from ſinne, Prou. 14.2.16. Iob. 1.1. It giueth true and inuincible fortitude in the midſt of the greateſt dangers, Pſal. 112.7. Exod. 18.21. Men of courage, &amp; fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring God, theſe two are ioyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. An example whereof we haue in <hi>Eliſha,</hi> 2. King. 6.16. and in <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> 2. Chron. 32.7. and in the Martyrs, who haue deſpiſed the threatnings of Tyrants, and haue remained vndaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the midſt of the flames: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Dauid</hi> grounded his courage, Pſal. 27.2. Pſal. 46.1.2.3. It is the way to true wiſedome, Prou. 1.7. Now all men deſire to be eſteemed wiſe.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, let vs call to minde the threatnings which God hath denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced againſt them which feare him not, Deut. 28.58.59. and againſt ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, Deut. 29.19.20.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, let vs conſider how dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous the eſtate of a ſecure man is, which chieflie appeareth in theſe
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:2933:90"/>three things: firſt, a ſecure man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoid of the feare of God, goes downe ſuddenly to hell, before he be aware, or can thinke of his miſerie, as <hi>Nabal</hi> died liked a ſtone, and as they in the daies of <hi>Noe,</hi> Matth. 24. and Luk. 27. euen whileſt they were eating and drinking and making merrie, were ouerwhelmed in the flood; ſo ſhall it be with the ſecure man. Secondly, he that feareth not God is very farre from true repentance; for not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his diſeaſe and wretched eſtate, he neuer dreaſnes of a remedy. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the longer he liues, the more he increaſeth his iudgement: as it is euident, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. 2.5.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="143" facs="tcp:2933:90"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>WHo ſhrugg'ſt vnſhelt'red, in the open, wide,</l>
                     <l>Cold, ſtaruing deſart of mans wofull ſtate,</l>
                     <l>Amid'ſt fell monſters, ſet on eu'ry ſide:</l>
                     <l>As head ſtrong Luſts, huge Pride and ougly Hate;</l>
                     <l>Toade-tonged Slaunders, greedie Couetiſe,</l>
                     <l>Diu'liſh Prophaneneſſe, tyrannizing Feare,</l>
                     <l>Wide-mouth'd deſpairing and that Cocatrice</l>
                     <l>Which deadly poyſ'neth all that commeth neere.</l>
                     <l>Who neere the brinke of that vnbottom'd pit</l>
                     <l>Of mazing horror, on the bleaker ſhore,</l>
                     <l>All nak'd and ſhudd'ring, doeſt forſaken ſit,</l>
                     <l>Hal'd by hell Porter to that diſmall doore.</l>
                     <l>Who art bedrinkled with the droppes that fall</l>
                     <l>Of wrath and anger, from th'offended God,</l>
                     <l>Threatning more tempeſts &amp; worſe ſtormes that ſhal</l>
                     <l>O'rewhelme thee grooueling, with their furious load.</l>
                     <l>Haſt hither: hide thee vnder this new roofe,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Newhowſe</hi> hath framed for thy ſure behoofe.</l>
                     <l>No ſtud is here, nor ſpar of any wood</l>
                     <l>Of Spoongy Sallow, or the Sappie ſhell,</l>
                     <l>Of crumbling ſhrublings, but what's firme and good:</l>
                     <l>As Oake of Baſhan and the Cedar Dele,</l>
                     <l>And ſeaſoned heart of Shittim, and ſuch ſtuffe</l>
                     <l>Which God's wide forreſt, ſacred Lebanon,</l>
                     <l>The holy Bible hath and yeelds inough,</l>
                     <l>To build ſafe refuge for each out-caſt one,</l>
                     <l>Who void of harbour ſtrayes and wanders wide.</l>
                     <l>For want of homeſtead, or a place t'abide.</l>
                     <l>Gods ſure <hi>Election</hi> as foundation ſtands.</l>
                     <l>Gods <hi>Feare</hi> as ſtrongeſt pillar beares vp all</l>
                     <l>The laſting building. <hi>Baptiſme</hi> is the band</l>
                     <l>That ioyntes each rafter to his principall.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Baptiſme</hi> the badge which beautifies the ſame.</l>
                     <l>With glorious var<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ſh while
<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>This hath refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to a ſermon of his touching the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, printed An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 1612.</note> 
                        <hi>Chriſts righteouſneſſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A roofe immortall, ſhelters all the frame</l>
                     <l>From dint of ſtormes and thunders eagerneſſe.</l>
                     <l>Here's <hi>Gods Election.</hi> Here's <hi>Gods Feare.</hi> Here is</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Baptiſme</hi> the ioy of Chriſtians. Here is plaine</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Chriſts</hi> perfect <hi>Goodneſſe, couering our amiſſe;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Which who once gets ſhall <hi>neuer looſe againe.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who then art wandring and would'ſt find a ſtay:</l>
                     <l>Who art vncou'red and would'ſt hide thy ſhame:</l>
                     <l>Who haſt no refuge for a ſtormy day:</l>
                     <l>Who ſeeſt thy death but can'ſt not ſhun the ſame:</l>
                     <l>Haſte hither: hide thee vnder this new reofe,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Newhowſe</hi> hath framed for thy ſure behoofe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Fowlke Robarts.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="144" facs="tcp:2933:91"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>REader: if weightie truth, with iudgement ſound,</l>
                     <l>In method moſt diſtinct, and order cleere,</l>
                     <l>Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauenly hart which did with grace abound,</l>
                     <l>In ſtile ſo plaine as to be wiſhed were,</l>
                     <l>If ſo great worth as is but rarely found,</l>
                     <l>May giue content, or pleaſe, all this is here:</l>
                     <l>If other things thou ſeekeſt, ſeeke elſe where.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Liue little booke, and long in price remaine:</l>
                     <l>Proſerue aliue thine Authors memorie:</l>
                     <l>Be to his friends in ſtead of picture plaine,</l>
                     <l>Where, not his face, but they his ſoule may ſee:</l>
                     <l>And reading, freſhly call to mind againe,</l>
                     <l>What grace, what ſpeech, what ſpirit, once had hee,</l>
                     <l>Too good (if God ſaw good) ſo ſoone to dye.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Dan. Heylet.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2933:91"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
